<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The craft and cruelty of the churches adversaries, discovered in a sermon preached at St. Margarets in Westminster, before the Honourable House of Commons assembled in Parliament. Novemb. 5, 1642. By Mathew Newcomen, minister of the Gospell at Dedham in Essex. Published by order of the House of Commons.</title>
            <author>Newcomen, Matthew, 1610?-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E128_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18223</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860369</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860369</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112489</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90061)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112489)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 23:E128[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The craft and cruelty of the churches adversaries, discovered in a sermon preached at St. Margarets in Westminster, before the Honourable House of Commons assembled in Parliament. Novemb. 5, 1642. By Mathew Newcomen, minister of the Gospell at Dedham in Essex. Published by order of the House of Commons.</title>
                  <author>Newcomen, Matthew, 1610?-1669.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 70, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.M. for Christopher Meredith, at the Sgne [sic] of the Crane in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLIII. [1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an order to print on verso of first leaf, dated 5 November 1642.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Novemb: 22".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Nehemiah IV, 11 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:112489:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Die Sabbathi,</hi> 5. Novemb: 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>SIR <hi>William Maſſam</hi> is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to return thanks to M. <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comen,</hi> for his great pains taken in the Sermon he this Day preached at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Margarets,</hi> at the intreaty of this Houſe, and to deſire him forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to print his Sermon, and to give a Coppy thereof to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for Religion, that when they ſhall have liberty to ſit, they may conſider by it, how to prepare and provide for the extirpation of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery; And it is further Ordered, that he ſhall have the uſuall privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for Printing his Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Hen: Elſyng,</hi> Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>

            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I Appoint <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith</hi> to Print this Sermon,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>MATH: NEVVCOMEN.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <postscript>
               <p>This is Entred,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>HEN: WALLEY.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112489:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CRAFT AND CRVELTY OF THE <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCHES ADVERSARIES,</hi> Diſcovered In a SERMON Preached at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garets</hi> in <hi>Weſtminster,</hi> before the Honourable HOUSE of COMMONS, Aſſembled in <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi> Novemb. 5, 1643.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Mathew Newcomen,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpell at <hi>Dedham</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Quid facit in Pectore Chriſtiano Luporum Feritas, Canum Rabies, Saevitia, Beſtiarum, Veneuum Lethale Serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum?</p>
               <bibl>Cyprian.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Cum ſitis Impij Crudeles, Homicidae, Inhumani, non am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius eritis Chriſtiani,</p>
               <bibl>Lucifer Calazit.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed by Order of the Houſe of COMMONS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith,</hi> at the Sgne of the Crane in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, M.DC.XLIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:112489:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112489:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE THE HOVSE OF COMMONS now Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F there be any <hi>Hiſtory</hi> in all the <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>God</hi> that may <hi>paralell</hi> our times, ſure it is this of <hi>Nehemiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> though delivered from their <hi>long</hi> and <hi>ſorrowfull captivity</hi> in <hi>Babylon:</hi> yet long it was ere they could ſee <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in their <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>God</hi> reedified, the <hi>worſhip</hi> of <hi>God</hi> reſtored, the <hi>walls</hi> of the <hi>holy Citty</hi> repaired, the <hi>Lords Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths</hi> ſanctified, the <hi>Prieſts</hi> in their <hi>ſeverall Orders</hi> and <hi>ſtations</hi> attending the <hi>ſervice</hi> of <hi>their God:</hi> Long it was ere matters of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> attained unto a <hi>Beautifull Regularity;</hi>
               <note place="margin">c <hi>Pembl.</hi>
               </note> ſome reckoning above a <hi>a 100.</hi> other above <hi>150.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Perk. <hi>Chronol. Red. cap.</hi> Anno. <hi>3431.</hi> Secundus <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> praefectus, Anno Mund. <hi>3537. Calvetius</hi> &amp; <hi>Helvicus,</hi> redit populi, <hi>3418.</hi> Secund <hi>Nehem.</hi> praefect. Anno <hi>3575.</hi>
               </note> ſome <hi>200. yeares.</hi>
               <note place="margin">d The vulgar <hi>Latine</hi> and the Engliſh <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va,</hi> make <hi>Ezra</hi> the writer of this Story, but it is a miſtake. Nehem. 1.1. See <hi>Pembl.</hi>
               </note> Three on ſets were given to this great work: <hi>thrice</hi> did the <hi>Lord</hi> raiſe up and employ bleſſed and glorious inſtruments in it before it arrived at it's <hi>perfection.</hi> The firſt was <hi>Zorobbabel, Ezra 1.</hi> The ſecond was <hi>Ezra, Ezra 7.</hi> The third was <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> of this <hi>Booke,</hi> according to the good hand of his God upon him,<note n="e" place="margin">Neh. 4.2, 3.</note> with <hi>invincible courage</hi> and <hi>indefatigable patience</hi> againſt the inſolent <hi>ſcoffes, multiplyed conſpiracies</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Cap. 4.8, 11. cap 6.2, 4.</note> and <hi>terrifying reports</hi> of his <hi>enemies,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Cap. 4. cap. 12. cap 6.6, 9.</note> againſt the <hi>treacheries</hi> of ſome of his owne <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Nobles,</hi> and their baſe <hi>compliances</hi> with the <hi>publick Adverſaries</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Cap. 3.5. cap. 6.10, 17.</note> againſt the <hi>murmurings</hi> of the <hi>people</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Cap. 4.10.5.1, 2, &amp;c.</note> with great <hi>expence</hi> of his <hi>eſtate</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Cap. 5.8, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18.</note> and <hi>hazard</hi> of his <hi>life</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Cap. 4.23.6.2.</note> carried on this great <hi>work,</hi> and gave it a <hi>full</hi> and <hi>bleſſed period,</hi> to the <hi>comfort</hi> of the <hi>Jewes</hi> and terrour of their <hi>enemies</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Chap. 6.16</note>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:112489:3"/>
            <p>To <hi>paralell</hi> this: the <hi>people</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> though through the <hi>mercy</hi> of <hi>God</hi> they have bin in a gracious meaſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from the ſpirituall <hi>Captivity</hi> of <hi>Romiſh Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> which our fore-Fathers were enthralled in ſo long a time; yet now <hi>almoſt a 100</hi> years have paſſed over us, ſince that <hi>firſt deliverance,</hi> and yet we ſee not that <hi>purity</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> that <hi>beauty</hi> of <hi>worſhip,</hi> that orderlines of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations, that <hi>ſtrength</hi> of <hi>diſcipline,</hi> as <hi>wals</hi> and <hi>bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks</hi> about this our <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which hath bin the <hi>deſire, prayer, expectation</hi> of us &amp; the ages that were before us. God ſeems to me to proceed by the ſame <hi>ſteps</hi> with us, that he did with the people of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and hath made <hi>3 viſible</hi> and <hi>memorable on-ſets</hi> upon the <hi>Reformation</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration</hi> of his Church among us. The firſt by that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Prince,</hi> the miracle and glory of his <hi>people</hi> &amp; <hi>age, Edward</hi> the <hi>6.</hi> of ever bleſſed memory, whoſe beginnings though exceeding <hi>hopeful</hi> and <hi>promiſing</hi> were ſoon ſtopt by acountermand, as it were from the God of Heaven, as <hi>Zerobabells</hi> beginnings were by letters from the King<note n="n" place="margin">Ezr 4.23, 24.</note>. Soon after the <hi>work</hi> was <hi>revived</hi> againe by his deare and gratious ſiſter Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in whoſe hands the Lord cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the worke to proſper to <hi>ſome further perfection,</hi> yet not unto that <hi>beauty</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> we hope our God intends to raiſe it to therfore this <hi>3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> time</hi> hath God raiſed up <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> for the advancing of this worke, even your ſelves, <hi>Honorable</hi> and <hi>Beloved:</hi> who though you have met with the ſame oppoſitions in this <hi>great imployment</hi> that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did: Malignant <hi>ſcoffs,</hi> bloudy <hi>conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, reports</hi> full of various <hi>terrours, deſertions</hi> of ſome of your <hi>Brethren, murmurings</hi> of not a few of the people: yet in the midſt of <hi>Armies</hi> and <hi>changes</hi> of <hi>Oppoſitions</hi> and <hi>diſcouragements,</hi> have hitherto with <hi>unwearied patience</hi> and <hi>undauntable Reſolutions,</hi> not without great <hi>expence</hi> of your <hi>eſtates</hi> and <hi>hazard</hi> of your
<pb facs="tcp:112489:3"/>
               <hi>lives,</hi> attended upon this worke now theſe two years. At the preſent to the great griefe of all loyall and honeſt hearts, we ſee you in the ſame poſture that <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and his aſsiſtants were, Cap. <hi>4.17. Every one with the one of his hands working, and with the other holding his weapon,</hi> a ſad condition: yet go on, the work of <hi>reforming</hi> the Church is Gods: he <hi>called</hi> you to it, <hi>he</hi> will <hi>maintain</hi> and defend you in it, he will give perfection to it, <hi>God</hi> is not as <hi>Man,</hi> that he ſhould begin to build, and not be able to finiſh.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſutableneſſe</hi> of this <hi>Hiſtory</hi> to our <hi>times,</hi> invited my thoughts (upon Summons received to this ſervice) to looke into this <hi>Book,</hi> and ſee if there were not ſomething there might <hi>fit</hi> the <hi>Day,</hi> and the ſutableneſſe of that por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Scripture, which is the <hi>Baſis</hi> of this enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe unto the Day, concluded my thoughts upon this Text. My <hi>deſire</hi> and <hi>prayer</hi> was, that I might ſpeake ſomething that <hi>might give glory</hi> to <hi>God</hi> for the <hi>mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold</hi> and <hi>great Deliverances</hi> he had <hi>wrought for us,</hi> and ſomething that might give <hi>encouragement to your ſelves</hi> in the great things you are to <hi>work for God.</hi> This latter part of my <hi>deſire</hi> was intercepted by a <hi>feare</hi> of conſuming too much of that <hi>time,</hi> which (though your <hi>Piety</hi> could willingly have beſtowed upon the <hi>worke of Praiſe-offering</hi>) yet the <hi>extreme neceſſities</hi> of State, could hardly <hi>ſpare.</hi> This made me <hi>ſilence,</hi> much of what I had <hi>prepared</hi> to <hi>ſpeake,</hi> both in the <hi>Explicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> and <hi>Applicatory</hi> parts of the <hi>Sermon:</hi> which yet (ſeeing it is your pleaſures to command what you heard to the Preſſe) waits now with the reſt upon you. I dare not thinke there is any thing,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> either in the one or in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that can <hi>adde</hi> unto your <hi>light:</hi> if any thing <hi>ſpoken</hi> or <hi>written</hi> may <hi>excite</hi> or <hi>encreaſe</hi> your <hi>heat,</hi> I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy much of the end I propounded in this Service. I dare not undertake to <hi>direct</hi> in any thing, if in any thing, I
<pb facs="tcp:112489:4"/>may <hi>erect</hi> your <hi>ſpirits</hi> in <hi>times</hi> ſo full of <hi>diſtempers,</hi> with a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> holy <hi>dedignation</hi> of all <hi>oppoſitions</hi> to carry on the great buſineſſe of the Lord Ieſus, in <hi>eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing Religion, Reforming the Church, rooting out Popery.</hi> I have enough, if I faile of this, it is the <hi>ſin</hi> of my <hi>infirmity,</hi> not my <hi>intention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luther</hi> in ſad tumultuous times was wont to ſay to his <hi>Brethren</hi> and thoſe about him, <hi>Come let us ſing the 40. Pſalme.</hi> Me thinkes you (Right Honourable) in theſe ſad conflicting times may ſay one to another, come let us reade the <hi>Booke of Nehemiah,</hi> there you may reade <hi>experiences, encouragements, quicknings, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, preſidents,</hi> to ſpread them before you is not the worke of an Epiſtle: nor is it needfull, having beene <hi>fully</hi> and <hi>excellently</hi> offered to your view in a Faſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gouge</hi> his Sermon.</note> onely this, as you have made the ſame preparations to this ſervice you are now upon,<note place="margin">Nehem. 1.</note> which <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did, addreſſing your ſelves thereunto by <hi>Faſting</hi> and <hi>Prayer:</hi> and have met the ſame <hi>varieties</hi> of <hi>oppoſitions</hi> and <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements,</hi> ſo <hi>perſiſting</hi> in the ſame pathes of <hi>Zeale</hi> for <hi>God, compaſſion</hi> to his <hi>Church, dependance</hi> on his <hi>power, adherence</hi> to his <hi>cauſe, conſtancy</hi> in his Service, Doubt not but the ſame mercifull hand of <hi>his</hi> and your <hi>God</hi> (after your <hi>Nehemiah</hi> like conflicts) ſhall <hi>crowne</hi> your <hi>faithfullneſſe</hi> with <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, which were ſo glorious, that <hi>when all their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies heard thereof,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nehem. 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>and all the</hi> Heathen <hi>round about, they were much caſt downe in their owne eyes, for they perceived that the worke was wrought of God.</hi> And they that are of you <hi>ſhall build the old waſte pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhall raiſe up the foundations of many Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 58.12.</note> 
               <hi>and yee ſhall be called the repairers of the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the reſtorer of paths to dwell in,</hi> which hath been and is, the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The leaſt and unworthieſt of your and the Churches ſervants. MATH: NEVVCOMEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112489:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached to the <hi>Honourable Houſe</hi> of Commons now aſſembled in PARLIAMENT. <hi>Novemb.</hi> the fifth, 1642.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>NEHEMIAH. 4.11.</bibl>
                  <p>And our adverſaries ſaid, they ſhall not know nor ſee till wee come in the midſt among them and ſlay them and cauſe the worke to ceaſe,</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His chapter gives you a veiw of the various diſcouragements, which that gracious man <hi>Nehemiah</hi> met in that glorious work of repayring <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and reſtoring the lapſed State of Church and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. Diſcouragements you ſhall behold in this chapter breaking in upon him like waves of the Sea, while he ſtands as a rock unbroken, unſhaken in the midſt of all. Like <hi>Iobs</hi> Meſſengers: before the firſt be diſpatched, there appears a ſecond before that be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, a third like <hi>Ezekiels</hi> propheſie, miſcheife,<note place="margin">Ezek. 7.</note> upon miſcheife and rumour upon rumour,</p>
            <p>In the firſt verſe, you have the adverſaries rage.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112489:5"/>
               <hi>When Sanballat heard that we built the wall, hee was wroth, and tooke great indignation.</hi> In the ſecond you have this rage venting it ſelfe in foame, in ſcoffs, and ſarcaſmes caſt upon <hi>Nehemiah</hi> his brethren, and their undertaking. <hi>What do thoſe feeble Jewes? will they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie themſelves? will they ſacrifice? will they make an end in a day &amp;c and Tobias ſaid, even that which they build, if a fox go up hee ſhall breake downe their ſtone wall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is the cooleſt of their rage, the heat of it reaches unto blood, ſo you find verſe the 7. and 8. <hi>When Sanballat and Tobiah, and the Arabians. &amp;c. heard that the walles of Jeruſalem were made up, they conſpired all of them together to come to ſight againſt Jeruſalem and to hinder it;</hi> Withall the people at the ſame time begin to murmur, verſe the tenth: <hi>And Judah ſaid the ſtrength of the bearers of burdens is decayed, and there is much rubbiſh, ſo that we are not able to build the wall.</hi> And this (as it is probable) gives incouragement to the adverſaries to antidate their triumph and glory, as if the Jewes had beene their requeſt, their prey already. <hi>And our adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſaid, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Diviſion of the Text.</note>In which words you may pleaſe to obſerve: Firſt, <hi>a ſtrong combination</hi> againſt the <hi>church</hi> of God. <hi>And our adverſaries ſaid.</hi> Secondly, <hi>a wicked deſigne</hi> they were combined in. <hi>To cauſe the work to ceaſe,</hi> this is firſt in their thoughts, though laſt in their words. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>a bloody meanes propounded,</hi> and agreed on for the accompliſhing of that deſign; and that is ſlaughter. <hi>Slay them, and cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</hi> Laſty, a ſubtile way projected for the effecting of that ſlaughter; <hi>we will come upon</hi> them ſecretly, ſuddenly, <hi>they ſhall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112489:5"/>neither know, nor ſee, till we are in the midſt of them, &amp; ſlay them, and cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</hi> I intend not to proſecute the particulars of the text, but to give you the ſum of the whole in one obſervation. <note place="margin">The Doctrine.</note> 
               <hi>The great deſigne of the enemies of the church, is by craft or cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or both, to hinder any worke that tends to the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or promoting of the churches good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the viſible enemies of the church of God, are but the <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> of Satan his agents: and therefore they obſerve his<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> methods, his rules of art in their attempts upon the church. Now as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan himſelf, ſometimes oppoſes the church by force, and then he is<note n="b" place="margin">Iſaia <hi>27.16.</hi> His allegoricis appellationibus figuratur ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limitas omnis tam ſpiritualis quam corporalis, quae adverſus deum ſe extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leret vi fraude vel utroque ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul. Iuni: ad locum. Eſai. <hi>34.16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>a piercing Serpent,</hi> and ſometimes circumvents the church by craft, and then hee is <hi>a crooked ſerpent, vel rectus venit, vel tortuoſus, vel leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem agit et ſaevit, vel draconem agit &amp; fallit.</hi> So doe his auxilliaries thoſe that fight under his colours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the churches peace and good, <hi>craft and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty</hi> are their chiefe engines of miſchiefe: and not one, but both they uſe, that as the ſcripture ſpeaks of thoſe birds of prey and deſolation, <hi>none of them ſhall want their mate.</hi> And as ſome write of the <hi>Aſp,</hi> he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wanders alone without his companion with him ſo the <hi>craft</hi> of the enemies of the church, is never but accompanied with <hi>cruelty,</hi> and their <hi>cruelty</hi> ſeldome without <hi>craft,</hi> and both bent to hinder any worke that tendes to the eſtabliſhment and promoting of the churches good.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Proved by Exemplificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> To give you ocular proofe of the <hi>crueltyes</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the enemies of the church have from time to time indeavoured to <hi>cauſe the worke to ceaſe,</hi> would be the buſineſſe, not of a <hi>ſermon,</hi> but of a <hi>volume,</hi> and yet eaſily done, had we but time, becauſe their <hi>cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:112489:6"/>ever appeares in its owne likeneſſe, in the ſhape of one of thoſe beaſts that <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw in his viſion, that <hi>had three ribs in the mouth of it, and they ſayd unto it, ariſe, devoure much fleſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 7.5.</note> You may trace the monſter foot by foot, from <hi>Abel</hi> unto this preſent in ſteps of blood. The perſecutions of the <hi>Jewiſh church</hi> under <hi>Pharoah. Nebuchadnezar, Antiochus,</hi> and of the <hi>chriſtian church</hi> vnder the <hi>heathen,</hi> and after them the <hi>Arrian Emperors</hi> and <hi>Biſhops:</hi> ſince them vnder <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi> on the one ſide, and the <hi>Turk</hi> on the other, are ſo knowne, I need not mention them: but this they all declare, that the <hi>indeavoures of the adverſaries,</hi> have alwayes bin by <hi>cruelty to cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</hi> And indeed if wee conſider thoſe floods and ſeas of blood, which in the ſucceſſive perſecutions of the church have beene exhauſted, wee may wonder the church is not quite extinct, ſave onely the bloud of Martyres, <hi>extra venas,</hi> is not <hi>cruor,</hi> but <hi>ſemen,</hi> and by <hi>the irradiation</hi> of the ſunn of righteouſneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes miraculouſly fruitfull to the producing of a new ſucceſſion of Saints.</p>
            <p>But to trace the adverſaries of the church in their craft,<note n="t" place="margin">Secondly of the oraft of headverſaries which are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall. Prov. 30.19.</note> 
               <hi>hic labor, hoc opus:</hi> they are <hi>ſerpentina ſoboles</hi> the ſeed of the ſerpent; <hi>and as the way of the ſerpent upon a rocke is unknowable,</hi> ſo are their wayes of undermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the church: yet as farre as either in hiſtory or ſcripture I may, I ſhall trace them, and give you a breife veiw of the ſeverall <hi>arts</hi> and <hi>crafts,</hi> whereby the <hi>adverſaries</hi> of the church have ſought to hinder their proceedings, and <hi>cauſe the work to ceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Firſt.</note> The firſt deſign that ever was againſt the Church of which we reade in Scripture is that of Pharaoh and his Councellors <hi>Exod.</hi> the firſt; <hi>Come let us deale
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112489:6"/>wiſely with them,</hi> and what is the reſult of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation? not to deny them preſently the liberty of their Religion we take away, but by burdening and oppreſſing them in their liberties and eſtates to breake their hearts and imbaſe their ſpirits, that they ſhould have no heart to minde Religion or any thing, becauſe of their great anguiſh and affliction. a deſigne that hath bin practiſed againſt the church of God many a time. Thus the <hi>Perſian</hi> Tyrant thought to have ſubdued the ſpirit of <hi>Hormiſdus</hi> that noble chriſtian. He would not kill him but enthrall him: Turne him out of his poſſeſſions, throw him from his honour, give his wealth, diguitie, wife, to the baſeſt of his ſlaves, Turne him naked our of dores to keepe Mules in the Wilderneſſe, by this meanes thinking to choke and ſmother that holy fire God had enkindled in his heart.</p>
            <p>And this is the art of the great <hi>Turke</hi> at this day though he pretend to let the Chriſtians in <hi>Greece</hi> and thoſe countries under him enjoy their lives and their <hi>religion,</hi> yet ſo heavy is his yoake upon them, that they have little joy of their lives, and for the moſt part as little care of their religion ſcarce any thing more than the <hi>name of Chriſt</hi> generally to be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Second.</note> The ſecond art whereby the adverſaries of the church have ſought to prejudice it, hath beene by procuring matches, and mixtures of ſome of the members of the church and ſome of their owne that were Idolaters. This was the art of <hi>Balaam,</hi> when hee ſaw hee could no otherwiſe faſten a curſe upon the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, he gave the <hi>King of Moab</hi> councell to enſnare the <hi>men of Iſrael</hi> with the <hi>daughters of Moab,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:112489:7"/>whereby they were drawne not onely to corporall, but to ſpirituall adultery. The hiſtory of this, you have <hi>Num.</hi> 25, 1, 2, 3. <hi>The people began to commit whoredome with the daughters of Moah, and the people did eat of their ſacrifices, and bowed downe to their gods, and Iſrael joyned himſelfe to Baal-Peor.</hi> And that this was the plot of <hi>Balaam</hi> is cleare, <hi>Numbers</hi> 31.16. <hi>Theſe cauſed the children of Iſrael through the councell of Balaam, to commit treſpafle againſt the Lord,</hi> It was <hi>Balams</hi> councell this, and wicked councell it was. This mixing with unbelievers hath bin ever looked upon as a thing of dangerous conſequence to the Church of God which is the reaſon that <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> was in ſuch a heat of indignation againſt the people for this thing. <hi>Nehe,</hi> 13.25, 26. ver. <hi>I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and curſed them, and ſmote certaine of them, and plucked off their haire and made them ſwear by God, ſaying, you ſhall not give your daughters to their Sonnes nor take their daughters unto your ſonnes, did not</hi> Salomon <hi>King of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſin by theſe thinge? yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many Nations there was no King like him who was beloved of his God, Nevertheleſſe even him did out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh women cauſe to ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Great dangers the Church of God is expoſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by this deſigne. Firſt, of being corrupted by this meanes, and drawne from the true Religion which is the very reaſon why God forbad ſuch marriages in the old law. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.4. <hi>For they will turne away thy ſonnes from following me that they may ſerve other Gods ſo will the anger of the Lord be kindled againſt you and deſroy thee ſuddainely.</hi> And ſad experience of this ſad effect and conſequent of marrying with Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and thoſe that are enemies to the Church, The
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112489:7"/>Church of God hath had not only in <hi>Salomon,</hi> whoſe heart his jd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>rous wives turned away from God and ſo capti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ted that he did publiquely tolerate their idolarour worſhip, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.4, <hi>When Salomon was cold his wives turned away his heart af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter other Gods,</hi> and verſ. 7. <hi>Then did Salomon build an high place for Chemoſh the abomination of Moah and for</hi> Moloch <hi>the abomination of Ammon,</hi> and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>did he for all his ſtrange wives and ſacrificed to their Gods.</hi> Nor onely in <hi>Iehoram</hi> the Son of <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat,</hi> the reaſon of whoſe deflection from the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of his father, and the principles of his education unto Idolatry is rendered by the holy ghoſt this, <hi>for the daughter of Ahab was hie wife,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8.18. Nor onely in other of the Kings of Iſrael and Judah, but even in chriſtian Kings and Princes, when they have matched though not with Pagans and Heathens but with ſuch as have profeſſed the chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, onely not in purity. <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperour was at firſt a true Orthodox Profeſſor, but being marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to an Arrian Lady ſhe ſoone inſnared him with her flatteries and captivated him to the ſame hereſie with her ſelfe, and he proved a moſt bloudy perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the true Orthodox Church.<note place="margin">Theod. 4.11</note>
            </p>
            <p>Or ſecondly, If there be ſuch eſtabliſhment of heart in the truth that the unbeliever dares not attempt to draw the believing yoak-fellow from the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or attempts it but in vaine. This inconvenience yet followes thereupon, that the unbeliever will as much as they can, <hi>viis et modis,</hi> promote the falſe Religion and ſubvert the true.</p>
            <p>The Church of God had experience of this in <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinian</hi> the Emperour,<note place="margin">Evagr. 4.10.</note> whoſe wife <hi>Theodora</hi> addicted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112489:8"/>to the hereſie of <hi>Eutyches,</hi> did no leſſe foſter, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage promote and reward the teachers &amp; maintainers of that hereſie than the Emperor did the true ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox profeſſors yea prevailed ſo farr with her husband as to make <hi>Severus,</hi> a chief leader of the <hi>Eutychian</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, By this meanes not only the preſent age but poſterity is indammaged. For put caſe the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving party doth ſurvice, there is danger leaſt the children (ſpecially if young) ſhould by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of an Idolatrous father or rhe perſwaſion of an Idolatrous mother to be drawn away from the true Religion. An inſtance of this we have in <hi>Valentinian</hi> the younger, whoſe father dying and leaving him in the tutelage of <hi>Juſtina</hi> his mother who was an Arrian (though all the time of her husbands life ſhee had concealed ir,<note place="margin">Socr. 5.2. Theod. 5.13.14. Sozom. 7.13.</note> knowing her husbands zeale for the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Religion) ſhe taking the advantage of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands death, and the tender and flexible age of her ſon to advance the Arrian faction eaſily corrupted him, that he was ſcarſe warme in his throne but he falls a perſecuting the true Religion. Theſe and many other inconveniences have bin obſerved to attend ſuch kinde of mixtures betweene the Church and their adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which the adverſaries are not ignorant of, and that is the reaſon ſometimes they are ſo willing to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their daughters in marriage to the members of the church,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 18.21.</note> but it is onely as Saul gave <hi>Michal</hi> unto Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>that ſhe might be a ſnare unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Third.</note> The third Art whereby the adverſaries of the church have endeavoured the ruine and over throw of Religon is by covering their intent to alter religion with a pretence of publick emollument, So <hi>Jeroboam</hi> to cover his Idolatrous projects, pretends the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112489:8"/>eaſe, <hi>It is too much for you to goe up to</hi> Jeruſalem, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.28. a great journey, a great charge, you may ſerve God nearer and better cheape at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethell,</hi> as if he meant not to alter Religion, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to let them have it with more <hi>eaſe</hi> and <hi>bettex accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation.</hi> Like that of ſome of late time: <hi>For people to heare two Sermons</hi> a day, <hi>it is too much,</hi> one well heard and remembred is enough: For young folke to be kept from ſports on the Lords Day, it is too much, <hi>It is too much for you to goe up worſhip at Ieruſalem.</hi> The like pretence was ſometimes uſed to <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> juſtly called <hi>Great,</hi> who having abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in <hi>Egypt</hi> their Heatheniſh ſacrifices, and forbid their Idolatrous worſhip, upon paine of conſiſcation and death; the people fearing the omiſſion of their accuſtomed ſuperſtitions, would make the River <hi>Nilus</hi> (whom they honoured as a God) keep in his ſtreames, and not water their land as in former yeares, began to mutinie, and things tended to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: whereupon the <hi>Preſident</hi> ofthe Countrey, wrote to the <hi>Emperour,</hi> beſeeching him <hi>for once to pleaſe the people, by conniving at their Idolatry.</hi> To whom he anſwered; <hi>It is better to continue faithfull and conſtant unto God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Soz.</hi> 7.20.</note> 
               <hi>then to preferre the overflowing of</hi> Nilus, <hi>and the fruitfullneſſe of the earth before piety and godlineſſe. Nay I had rather</hi> Nilus <hi>ſhould never flow, then to have it raiſed by ſacrifices and inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> A brave reſolution, and becomming a true Chriſtian Prince. Let people be pleaſed or diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, come loſſe, come gaine, <hi>let truth and godlineſſe be maintained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A fourth fraud or art whereby they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſupplant the Church, is, By coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112489:9"/>a friendly compliance with the Church of God, as if they meant to help and farther the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes thereof, when in truth, they intend nothing but to overthrow and hinder all. So the <hi>Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Eſra.</hi> 4. When the people of God were about rebuilding the Temple, the Adverſaries came and offered to joyne with them. <hi>verſ.</hi> the ſecond. <hi>Let us build with you, for we ſeek your God as you doe.</hi> When they intended nothing more then to betray them. This was the great art of the <hi>Adverſaries</hi> in the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> dayes, when many falſe bretheren joyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 2.</note> meerely to ſpy out their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and many <hi>falſe Apostles</hi> that ſeemed to preach <hi>Chriſt</hi> with abundance of zeale and forwardneſſe, but it was only that they might withdraw Diſciples from the <hi>true Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Apostles</hi> of the <hi>Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> and fill the <hi>Church</hi> with <hi>rents and ſchiſmes,</hi> as they did the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Corinth.</hi> Thus the <hi>Arrians</hi> would often counterfeit themſelves <hi>Orthodox</hi> men, and mingle themſelves with <hi>Orthodox</hi> profeſſers, that they might with leſſe ſuſpition, ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their errors. That good Prince <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, was much abuſed by that Generation in this kind, his great admirer <hi>Euſchius,</hi> confeſſeth he retained neare him. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>de vita</hi> Conſtantin. 4.54.</note> 
               <hi>Sceleratos Nebulenes qui ſimulaverunt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionem Chriſteanam.</hi> Specially one potorious one, who had bin <hi>Chaptain</hi> to the <hi>Emperours Siſter</hi> and by her dying, was commended to the <hi>Emperour,</hi> and received into his Family, and though all the time of <hi>Conſtantine the great,</hi> he kept his poiſon hid; yet no ſooner was he dead, but he began to play his pranks. Firſt inveigling the chiefe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112489:9"/>bed chamber,</hi> then <hi>ſome of the reſt,</hi> after theſe the <hi>Empreſse,</hi> and ſoon after the <hi>Emperour himſelfe;</hi> winning them all to the <hi>Arrian hereſy:</hi> who if in <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time he had not complyed with the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox</hi> party, he had never had the acceſſe to <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> and ſo never this opporrunity of ſpreading that <hi>hereſie.</hi> This is a trick not unuſuall with <hi>Rome,</hi> I have heard that the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> have a practiſe of running over to the <hi>Lutheran Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">I find a paſſage in <hi>Frantrius,</hi> that may give ſome credit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this. <hi>Oracula Sacra.</hi> 129. p. 842.</note> pretending to be converts, and to <hi>build with them,</hi> but it is only to keep up that bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contention that is between the <hi>Calvinists</hi> and the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> the <hi>virulency</hi> whereof, is much fomented by theſe <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>negado Ieſuits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt way is. To <hi>ingratiate</hi> themſelves to <hi>Kings and Princes,</hi> with much officiouſneſſe and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended care of their profit and honour, that ſo being <hi>potent</hi> with the <hi>Potentates</hi> of the earth, they may have the more power to doe the Church a miſchiefe. So the <hi>Adverſaries</hi> of the <hi>Iews</hi> pretended, that in <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>conſcience,</hi> they could doe no leſſe then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of the <hi>Iewes</hi> to King <hi>Artaxerſes,</hi> Ezra 4.14. <hi>Now becauſe we have maintenance from the Kings pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and it was not meet for us to ſee the King diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, we have ſent and certified the King.</hi> Wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that cared no more for the <hi>Kings honour</hi> then a <hi>ſtraw,</hi> only pretend this, that they might the more eaſily <hi>draw out</hi> the Kings power, for the ſuppreſſing of the <hi>Church:</hi> So <hi>Haman, Eſth.</hi> 3.8. ſeemed to mind only <hi>the Kings profit,</hi> when his mind is only ſet upon the <hi>Iewes</hi> deſtruction. <hi>It is not for the Kings profit to ſuffer them.</hi> So the <hi>Iewes</hi> themſelves in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting and murdering the Lord <hi>Christ,</hi> pretend nothing but <hi>loyalty and reſpect to</hi> Caeſar. <hi>We have no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112489:10"/>King but</hi> Caeſar. <hi>And if thou let this man go, thou art not</hi> Caeſars <hi>friend.</hi> So that <hi>Arrian</hi> Prieſt, of whom I was even now ſpeaking, that corrupted <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius,</hi> the ſonne of the great <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe firſt into the favour of that young <hi>Prince</hi> by his officiouſneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Soz 8.1.</note> in carrying his <hi>Fathers will to him,</hi> and the advantage that he made of his favour, was to corrupt and poyſon him. It hath alwayes bin obſerved, that the greateſt <hi>Heretikes,</hi> have bin the greateſt <hi>Courtiers.</hi> The <hi>Arrians</hi> in their age, and of them <hi>the Ieſuites learned it,</hi> and of the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians.</hi> All of them have made it their <hi>maſter-piece,</hi> to inſinuate themſelves into the favour of <hi>Princes,</hi> and then make bold with their power, for the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the truth.</p>
            <p>A ſixt ſtratagem of theirs is, To charge the Truth and Profeſſours of it with falſe accuſations, thereby to render them odious, either to Princes or people. So the <hi>Goſpell of Chriſt</hi> was called <hi>hereſie, Paul a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent fellow, and a mover of Sedition.</hi> So <hi>Ezra</hi> 4. The King is told, if the <hi>Iewes</hi> rebuild the wall, they will pay no tole nor tribute.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ozom <hi>2 24.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heod <hi>1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocrat. <hi>1.21.</hi> Athan Ep. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olit vitam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gintes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ozom. <hi>2.8.</hi>
               </note> So the <hi>Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> had horrible unnameable crimes, laid to their charges. Thus the <hi>Arrians</hi> charged <hi>Athanaſias</hi> with <hi>Adultery, Murther, Witch-craft.</hi> Thus the <hi>Iewes</hi> of <hi>Perſia,</hi> in the time of <hi>Sapores,</hi> accuſed <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sileucia,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>as a friend of the Romane Emperours, and one that gave intelligence to them of the Perſian affaires,</hi> which was the occaſion, not only of the death of <hi>Simeon,</hi> but of a generall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution againſt the whole Church. Thus deale the Jeſuites with the Proteſtants. And thus the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112489:10"/>of the power of godlineſſe, charge it with Hereſie, Faction, Rebellion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Willets</hi> Pillars of Papiſtry. Ger. <hi>Con Cath. l.</hi> 1 <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note> and all that will make it odious, either to Prince or people.</p>
            <p>The 7<hi rend="sup">h</hi>. way is, By procuring and enacting <hi>Lawes,</hi> whereby they may either <hi>inſnare the conſciences</hi> or <hi>the lives</hi> of the people of God unawares. Such as that was <hi>Daniel</hi> 6.7. when they come and tell the King, <hi>All the Preſidents of the Kingdome, the Governours and Princet, Councellours and Captaines, have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted together to ſtabliſh a royall Statute. That who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall aske any Petition of God or man, ſave of thee ô King, for thirty dayes, ſhall be caſt into the Lyons Den. Darius</hi> was newly aſcended upon the Throne, and his Princes ſeemed to have ſtudied no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but the increaſing of his <hi>power</hi> and <hi>might,</hi> they pretend it will much adde to his <hi>magnificence,</hi> and ſtrike a greater awe into the hearts of his new conquered Subjects, if ſuch a Law as this be made. Now <hi>when all the Preſidents, and Councellours and Governours ſhall commend</hi> a thing to the King, as the unanimous <hi>reſult of all their councels,</hi> and deſire ſuch a Law to be made for the Kings <hi>Majeſty</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> it is eaſily obtained, though their deſigne was by this Law to enſnare the people of God, either to wound their conſciences, by making them ſin, in neglecting that duty of worſhip they owed to God, or elſe to cut off their lives in the purſuance of that worſhip. The King could not find this out, nor it may bee moſt of the common ſort of the Jewes: but <hi>Daniel</hi> did, and reſolved rather to <hi>tranſgreſſe the Lawes of the King,</hi> then the <hi>Law of God,</hi> rather to be caſt into the <hi>Den of Lyons,</hi> then to carry about a <hi>Lyon in his boſome,</hi> even <hi>an inraged conſcience.</hi> So <hi>Iulian</hi> that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112489:11"/>ſubtill enemy of the Church of God, inſnared the poore Chriſtians unawares, for calling his Souldiers to appeare before him, that they might receive their pay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theod.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5, 16</note> he cauſed an Altar with fire upon it to be ſet by, and a Table of Incenſe, and commanded every ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, as he came to receive his money, to caſt ſome Incenſe into the fire upon the Altar, which ſome of his <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſouldiers underſtanding to be an <hi>impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite</hi> and <hi>interpretative Idolatry,</hi> refuſed to doe, and would rather looſe their pay: others not knowing the depth and myſtery of this i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iquity, ſuſpecting no hurt, did it, and ſo defiled their conſciences; which filled them afterwards with ſuch extreme griefe and horrour, when they came to the knowledge of it, as they did <hi>offer to expiate their ſinne with their blood.</hi> Had <hi>Darius</hi> knowne, that the intent of his Princes, in that which they called their Royall <hi>Law,</hi> had been to intrap the life of <hi>Daniel,</hi> he would never have ſigned it. Had the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> knowne, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of <hi>Iulian,</hi> in commanding them to ſprinkle ſome Incenſe upon the burning Altar, had been to make them deny the Faith, they would never have done it. But this is the <hi>craft of the Adverſaries,</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and enact Lawes, that may <hi>looke one way,</hi> and <hi>ſtrike another,</hi> that may ſeeme to be for <hi>Majeſty,</hi> or <hi>Honour,</hi> or <hi>Decency;</hi> but are indeed for <hi>the inſnaring</hi> and <hi>ſupplanting</hi> of the Church of God.</p>
            <p>Another way is, By ſecret conſpiracies and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous combinations againſt the Church, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and ruine it. So here <hi>Nehem.</hi> 4.7, 8. <hi>The</hi> Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians <hi>and the</hi> Ammonites <hi>and the</hi> Aſhdodites, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire all of them together, to come and fight againſt</hi> Jeruſalem. So <hi>Pſa.</hi> 83.3. <hi>They take crafty counſell
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112489:11"/>againſt thy people, and conſpire againſt thy hidden ones, they have conſulted together with one conſent, they are confederate againſt thee:</hi> Gebal <hi>and</hi> Ammon <hi>and</hi> Amalek, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So <hi>Act.</hi> 23.12, 13. <hi>Certaine of the Iewes banded themſelves together, and bound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under a curſe, ſaying, that they would neither eat nor drinke, till they had killed</hi> Paul. Such was the Str<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tagem of our Adverſaries, the deliverance from which, we celebrate this day, a conſpiracy of men, that had bound themſelves by a curſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy us, and had not only <hi>ſaid,</hi> but <hi>ſworne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Doctrin proved by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. 1. Drawn from the Adverſaries 1. Hatred of the Church.</note> 
               <hi>Wee will come upon them, and they ſhal neither know nor ſee, til we are in the midſt of them and ſlay them, and cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</hi> Their deſigne was by craft and cruelty, to diſturbe and deſtroy the Churches peace.</p>
            <p>And truth is, in Reaſon we can looke for no other, if we conſider the innate diſpoſition of the enemies of the Church.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in regard of that implacable hatred the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries beare unto the Church. It is a true ſaying, <hi>Odia Religionum ſunt acerbiſsima,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Immortale o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium &amp; nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſanabile bellum. Ardet ad-huc combos. &amp; Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyra ſummus u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>. Inde ſuror v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go quod Numi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na vicinorum. Odit uter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, cum ſolos credat habendos Eſſe Deos quos ipſe colit. <hi>Juve. Sat. 15.</hi> Omnis Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio quae Dei cauſâ ſuſcipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſtabilis ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura eſt &amp; diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turna. <hi>Druſ. Apotheg.</hi>
               </note> Hatred grounded in differences of Religion, are the moſt bitter and uncapable of Reconciliation. And it is a true obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of ſome<note n="b" place="margin">D. <hi>Day</hi> upon. 1 Cor. 16.9.</note>, that the nearer any are unto a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction</hi> in matters of Religion, and yet ſome <hi>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> retained, the <hi>deeper</hi> is the <hi>hatred;</hi> as he obſerves a <hi>Iew</hi> hates a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> worſe then he doth a <hi>Pagan</hi> or a <hi>Turke;</hi> a <hi>Papiſt</hi> hates a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> worſe then he doth a <hi>Iew;</hi> and a <hi>Formaliſt</hi> hates a <hi>Puritan</hi> worſe then he doth a <hi>Papiſt. No ſuch hatred</hi> under Heaven (ſaith he) as that between a Formaliſt and a Puritan. Now <hi>Truth</hi> being <hi>one,</hi> the true Religion <hi>one,</hi> and this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112489:12"/>the <hi>poſſeſsion</hi> and <hi>profeſſion</hi> of the true Church, this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth all the world againſt it, <hi>Pagans, Iewes, Turks, Papists, Formaliſts;</hi> that as they every one <hi>Idolize</hi> their owne Religion and opinion, and ſeeke to <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe</hi> each other, ſo they all <hi>combine,</hi> to ſuppreſſe the true Religion, to keepe that from flouriſhing, from ſhining forth in it's originall beauty and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>And then ſecondly are full of craft.<note place="margin">2 Craft.</note> 
               <hi>The ſeed of the Serpent,</hi> for ſo God cals them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. thereby letting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us know, <hi>That as the Serpent was moae ſubtill then any beaſt of the field,</hi> Geneſ. 3.1. So the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries</hi> of the Church <hi>are more ſubtile then all the men of the world,</hi> whereas the Church of God, they are the <hi>Seed of Iacob,</hi> Pſal. 22.23.<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 25.27.</note> 
               <hi>He was a plaine man, Sine fraude &amp; fuco,</hi> and ſo are <hi>his Seed, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiam habent, fraudulentiam horrent,</hi> but their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries they are full of<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal 83.3. Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 15.35. Pſal. 10.7. Pſal. 119.110.</note> 
               <hi>craft,</hi> therfore ſometimes in Scripture called Foxes<note n="b" place="margin">Cant. 2.15. Luk 13.12.3. Cruelty.</note>.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And as full of <hi>cuelty</hi> as <hi>craft,</hi> therefore in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture proclaimed <hi>bloudy</hi> as well as<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 55.23.</note> 
               <hi>deceitfull men.</hi> And in that reſpect compared to<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 22.12, 13, 16, 21.</note> 
               <hi>Lyons, Bulls, Doggs, Vnicornes,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 10.16. Act. 20.19.</note> 
               <hi>Wolves.</hi> The Churches <hi>enemies</hi> are men of <hi>cruell bloudy</hi> diſpoſitions, ſuch as was <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt of <hi>France,</hi> whoſe rage againſt the truth of God, and the Reformation in <hi>Luthers</hi> time, was ſo bloudy, that he did in a ſolemne aſſembly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. <hi>If he knew any part of his body infected with that contagion</hi> (<hi>of</hi> Lutheraniſme) <hi>hee would preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teare it from him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Si quam ſui Corporis par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem iſtâ Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagione ſciret infectam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſurum illico nelongiùs ſerperet. <hi>Sleid. com. lib. 9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that it might ſpread no further.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:112489:12"/>Or that of the <hi>Germain Count Felix</hi> of <hi>Wartenburge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A memorable thing fell cut, <hi>anno</hi> 1550. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men being at Supper toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hotrible things againſt the Profeſſours of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, among the reſt <hi>Count Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix</hi> of <hi>Warten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge</hi> a great Warriour, and that had bin in place of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand under <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Emperour, ſaid he hep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ere he died to ride up to the ſpurrs in the bloud of the <hi>Lutherans;</hi> but being ſmitten by God, that very night, he fell a blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in that violent manner, that his blood choaked him and he dyed. <hi>Flac. Illyr.</hi> So let all thine enemies periſh ô Lord, and give them blood to drinke, <hi>for they are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Who,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ped ere he dyed, to ride up to the ſpurrs in the bloud of the</hi> Lutherans. Theſe are the diſpoſitions of them all,<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 27.29.</note> for as <hi>face anſwers to face in water, ſo the heart of man to the heart of man.</hi> Now looke upon the <hi>Adverſaries of the Church</hi> thus, as full of innate <hi>craft, cruelty, malignity</hi> againſt the Church of God and the true Religion, and what can you expect, but that they ſhould by all deceitfull, bloudy wayes, hinder and oppoſe any worke that tends to the ſtabliſhment and promoving of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches good.</p>
            <p>But if you adde to this,<note n="a" place="margin">Reaſon drawne from the power of Satan in the hearts of the Adverſaries.</note> the mighty power that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan hath in the hearts of the <hi>Churches enemies,</hi> to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of whom it may be applyed, which <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ananias, Satan hath filled thy heart,</hi> yea <hi>Satan</hi> hath not onely <hi>filled</hi> them, but as the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> in one word tels us,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ioh. 6.44.</note> is <hi>continually active</hi> and <hi>mighty in them.</hi> And againe tels us, they are as ſpontaneouſly ſubject to his power and motions. That <hi>native malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, craft, cruelty,</hi> that is inherent in the Churches <hi>Adverſaries</hi> is <hi>principle</hi> enough to carry them on in deſignes againſt the Churches good, though <hi>Satan</hi> ſhould never incite them; and that <hi>power</hi> and <hi>energy</hi> of <hi>Satan</hi> in them, is enough to carry them in that way, though there were no ſuch <hi>naturall diſpoſition.</hi> But when <hi>both</hi> meet, a ſtrong <hi>propenſion</hi> of nature in themſelves, and a mighty energeticall power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112489:13"/>over them, needs muſt they with moſt impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous violence be carried on by any <hi>craft</hi> or <hi>cruelty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Reaſon from Gods permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this. 1. For his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Tryall.</note> no matter what or how to hinder all that tends to the Churches good. They having an act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vity of their owne that way, and Satan who is mighty in them, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them that way too.</p>
            <p>True it is, God could reſtraine the rage of his Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> bind downe the <hi>malignity</hi> of their natures (though he leave it in them) with a band of braſſe or iron, as the ſtump of that tree in <hi>Nebuchadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars</hi> viſion, and retund even the Devills owne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice. But it pleaſeth the wiſedome of God to give ſcope thus to the malice of Satan and his inſtruments, and that both, in reference to his people, and to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>To his people. Firſt, for their tryall, the reaſon the Apoſtle gives, why the Lord permits hereſies in his Church, may let us ſee why the Lord ſuffers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oppoſition againſt his Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19.<note n="a" place="margin">Vt qui proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſunt &amp; haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoes fermento ſe non in ece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt manifeſti fiant in Nobis. Profi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iant in cognitio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceant in confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione, o len lunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſidem ſuam, conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian veritatem opera, ut glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rificetur Pater noſter qui in coelis eſt. <hi>Cram. Haereſiolog.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>There muſt be alſo hereſies among you, that they which are approved may be made manifeſt among you</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Cum Eccleſia pace &amp; con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diâ fruitur, nec afflictione ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ùs aut diſsenſione in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecùs labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, qui Chriſti ſunt non agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur, vix<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſeipſos invicem dignoſcunt quia prosperitatis tempore facile eſt Deo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ervire <hi>Camer</hi> in <hi>Joh. 6.</hi>
               </note>. Who will not owne the Churches cauſe, when it proſpers, meets with no oppoſition?<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſeph. Antiq. l.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 8. 2 For his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples exerciſe.</note> The <hi>Samaritans</hi> were wont to challenge kindred of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> when the ſtate of the <hi>Iewes</hi> flouriſhed, but when it was afflicted then diſclaimed them. <hi>Many</hi> will <hi>imbarke</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the <hi>Churches</hi> cauſe in a <hi>calme,</hi> that with the <hi>Souldiers</hi> in the <hi>Acts</hi> will fly out of the Ship in a <hi>ſtorme.</hi> Therefore that his owne which are appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved may be manifeſted, God ſuffers Satan and his inſtruments to oppoſe, to uſe all their <hi>craft</hi> and <hi>cruelty</hi> to hinder his <hi>Churches</hi> good.</p>
            <p>And not onely that his people may be <hi>tryed,</hi> but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112489:13"/>alſo <hi>exerciſed</hi> in <hi>ſwiſdome, faith, patience, courage.</hi> When there was deliberation at <hi>Rome</hi> about the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhing of <hi>Carthage</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Sinenda eſt Carthago ut e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus metu diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plina à majori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus tradita jam Laba, cens re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt ituatur. <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian</hi> de bellis puntcis.</note>, let it <hi>ſtand</hi> ſaith <hi>Scipio,</hi> leaſt the people of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould want an occaſion or object whereon to exerciſe their valour. God could ſoone <hi>annihilate</hi> his <hi>Churches enemies;</hi> but let <hi>them live,</hi> ſaith God, let them doe their worſt, they ſhall but be for the exerciſe of my peoples wiſdome, faith, zeale, conſtancy, courage and whole panoplie of grace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. For the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther illuſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his owne Glory.</note>And yet God hath a further <hi>end</hi> in permitting this, then his <hi>peoples exerciſe and tryall,</hi> and that is, <hi>The illuſtration of his owne glory,</hi> by the <hi>crafty</hi> and <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> attempts of the <hi>Churches enemies,</hi> that the glory of his wiſdome and power in the preſervation and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of his <hi>Church</hi> might be the more illuſtrious. <hi>Archimedes</hi> had never been ſo famous, if the City where he dwelt had not been ſo long ſo violently beſieged, and a long time preſerved onely by his meanes. <hi>If the Church of God, the city of the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his holineſſe,</hi> ſhould not often be ſurrounded with enemies, beſieged with difficulties and oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the wiſdome and power of God, in preſerving and proſpering his <hi>Church,</hi> would never be ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, therefore the Lord ſuffers the <hi>Adverſaries of his Church to deſigne</hi> and indeavour by <hi>craft</hi> or <hi>cruelty,</hi> or both, to hinder any worke that tends to the Churches good, gives them leave to plot and conſpire againſt his Church, <hi>and lets them ſay. They ſhal not know nor ſee, til wee are in the midſt of them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Doctrine applyed. 1 By way of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration.</note>And now if ever Text were <hi>verbum diei,</hi> as the vulgar Latine reades it, or <hi>verbum ſuper
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112489:14"/>rotas,</hi> as ſome others: Surely this Truth, this Text is ſuch. Every word of this Text is a <hi>Wheele</hi> of that triumphant Chariot,<note place="margin">Pro. 25 11. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Mercer.</hi>
               </note> in which our Church and State this day glories over a deſigne of our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> againſt us, fraught with all the ſubtilty and cruelty, that hell it ſelfe was able to infuſe into it, <hi>This day thirty ſeven yeares, was this Scripture fulfilled in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>This day thirty ſeven yeares, the King then ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon the Throne, had ſummoned the <hi>Peeres</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> of this Kingdome to an Aſſembly of <hi>Parliament.</hi> The intent of that meeting (as was hoped by Gods people, and feared by their enemies) was to ſurround <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the Temple, with walls and bulwarkes, to ſecure the <hi>Church,</hi> the true Religion and worſhip of God, with needfull, healthfull Lawes: this was the worke intended. Wherefore ſhould a Parliament meet, but for that worke? and our <hi>Adverſaries ſaid, they ſhall not know, neither ſee till we are in the midſt of them and ſlay them, and cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">And our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaris.</note> 
               <hi>Our Adverſaries:</hi> Who are they? Conſider and then judge. <hi>Who are they</hi> that (when time was) filled their loathſome Priſons with the bodies of our <hi>fore-Fathers?</hi> Made our land drunk with the bloud of <hi>Martyrs?</hi> In the ſpace of leſſe then 4. yeares ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed the lives<note n="*" place="margin">Balthaz. Hol. in Chron. &amp; Oſiand. Cen. <hi>16</hi> Hiſtor. Eccleſ. Anno <hi>1555.</hi>
               </note> of 800. <hi>Innocents</hi> unto their Idols? And ever ſince God hath put a ſtop to thoſe bloudy outrages have <hi>travailed</hi> with nothing but <hi>Englands deſtruction</hi> now theſe <hi>Foureſcore</hi> yeares? <hi>Who are they</hi> that have made ſo many <hi>deſparate stabbes</hi> at the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112489:14"/>breaſts of our <hi>Prineces?</hi> ſo many <hi>deadly blowes</hi> at the <hi>heart</hi> of the <hi>State?</hi> given <hi>life</hi> and <hi>vigour</hi> to ſo many <hi>inſurrections</hi> and <hi>rebellions</hi> in the bowells of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? Are they not the <hi>Papiſts?</hi> It is eaſie then to point out theſe <hi>Adverſaries.</hi> The <hi>Papiſts:</hi> they are our <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> ſo they have beene, ſo they are, ſo they will be, as long as Chriſt is ours, his Goſpell ours, the Reformed Religion ours. Sooner ſhall a man finde honey and balme in the neſts of <hi>Aſpes,</hi> and the <hi>Dennes</hi> of <hi>Dragons,</hi> then wee true friendſhip and peace with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.<note place="margin">Said.</note> Sooner ſhall Eaſt and Weſt meete and kiſſe, the <hi>Arke</hi> and <hi>Dagon, Hieruſalem</hi> and <hi>Babylon, Christ</hi> and <hi>Belial</hi> ceaſe to be Adverſe, then they ceaſe to be our <hi>Adverſaries. Theſe were, theſe are our Adverſaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And our <hi>Adverſsaries ſaid.</hi> Theſe <hi>our Adverſaries</hi> had had many a <hi>ſaying</hi> to us, they had ſaid in eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty eight,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal 83 4.</note> 
               <hi>Come and let us cut them off from being a Nation, that the name of</hi> England <hi>may be no more in remembrance.</hi> They had ſaid, as <hi>Moab</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2 Kin. 3.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Up <hi>Rome,</hi> to the ſpoyle, preſuming the victory was theirs before the fight. And when that <hi>Saying</hi> was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed, yet they <hi>ſaid</hi> there was a <hi>day</hi> a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming which <hi>ſhould pay for all,</hi> that was the day of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> death, concerning which their <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lams</hi> propheſied,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Parſons</hi> anſ. to the libell of <hi>Eng Iuſt. p.</hi> 176 181.</note> 
               <hi>That by the uncertainty of the next heire the Kingdome was in a deſpeat caſe, in the greateſt miſery that ever it was, ſince or before the Conqueſt, and farre worſe then any Countrye in Chriſtendome</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Cujus ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrum velut to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Regni vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raginem &amp; naufrrgium, tanquam ſub o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemini:—In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentes moles tempeſtatum &amp; conturbatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, cruento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum imbrium conglomeratas nubes veſtris impendere cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicibus deſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etis. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Anglia in praedam expeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur. <hi>Weſton</hi> de triplici ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis, officio: in perorat ad Academ.</note> 
               <hi>That Clouds of blood hung over</hi> England, <hi>which waited but her diſſolution for their diſſolving, that upon her death</hi> England <hi>would</hi> be <hi>a common prey, and her tombe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112489:15"/>would be</hi> Englands <hi>grave.</hi> This our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> ſaid then, and from theſe ſayings, iſſued all that prodigious variety of murderous complotments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſacred perſon of that ever honoured <hi>Queen,</hi> The <hi>miracle</hi> of her <hi>Sex,</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of her <hi>Age,</hi> the <hi>aſtoniſhment</hi> of the <hi>World.</hi> But the ſilver line of her pretious life being <hi>hid in the hollow of Gods hand</hi> from all their deſperate aſſaſſinates, ſhe <hi>full of yeares,</hi> and more full of <hi>honour,</hi> went to the grave in peace: and God who <hi>fruſtrates the tokens of the Lyars,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 44.25.</note> 
               <hi>and makes Diviners mad,</hi> contrary to the hopes and confidences of our <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> brought in a peacefull <hi>King,</hi> and eſtabliſhed his Throne in peace.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Say our Adverſaries</hi> now? are they not ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed and confounded in their former diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as they can open their mouths no more? No, they are <hi>ſaying</hi> ſtill, the malice of our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> is as uncapable of diſheartning, as <hi>Balaam</hi> was in his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of curſing <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Let God appeare never ſo often againſt them, let the <hi>Angell of God</hi> ſtand with a drawn Sword in his hand, they will on, yet again <hi>our Adverſaries ſaid,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaid to his Servants, that our <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> ſaid one to another,<note place="margin">Exod. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Come let us deale wiſely,</hi> our former projects againſt this people, have bin too ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and open, our <hi>preparations</hi> in 88. proclaimed <hi>our intentions,</hi> and made them <hi>fruſtrate,</hi> the <hi>treaſons</hi> of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Lopez, Sanders,</hi> &amp;c. were <hi>common, ordinary</hi> and <hi>poore</hi> attempts, now for ſome <hi>rare ſtratagem,</hi> ſome <hi>depth</hi> of <hi>darknes,</hi> ſome <hi>mystery of unheard of treachery,</hi> that may be <hi>acted</hi> by <hi>unſeene inſtruments,</hi> they <hi>ſhall neither know nor ſee, till wee are in the middeſt among them.</hi> And what was this, but the <hi>Pouder-Treaſon.</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:112489:15"/>Looke upon the cunning projecting and carrying on that <hi>Treaſon,</hi> you will heare our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> ſaying. <hi>They ſhall neither know nor ſee till we are in the midst of them.</hi> And looke upon their bloudy intent in it. <hi>And it was to ſlay and cauſe the worke to ccaſe</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">They ſhall not know.</note>Firſt for the <hi>crafty projecting and managing the plot,</hi> becauſe they will make ſure, we ſhall <hi>know nothing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> none ſhall be admitted to conſultation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the thing, but thoſe that will by <hi>Vowes</hi> and <hi>Oathes,</hi> and <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and <hi>all that is Sacred,</hi> binde <hi>themſelves</hi> more then once,<note n="a" place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> his Speech at the arraignement of <hi>Garnet.</hi>
               </note> neitheir <hi>directly</hi> nor <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly,</hi> neither <hi>plainly</hi> nor by <hi>circumſtance to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the plot.</hi> Hence it was that in two yeares ſpace (for ſo long was this Treaſon forming) not the leaſt inckling of it came to any of our eares, <hi>our Adverſaries had ſworne, They ſhall not know,</hi> and if ever they were true to their <hi>Oathes</hi> it was here. <hi>They ſhall not know.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor ſee.</hi> Therefore all their worke lyes <hi>under ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nor ſee.</note> and is diſpatched <hi>in the night, when deepe ſleepe falls upon men:</hi> If either the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the night, or the depth of the earth can hide it, <hi>wee ſhall not ſee.</hi> And how did <hi>God</hi> for a while ſeeme to ſmile upon their <hi>project,</hi> and to <hi>facillitate</hi> their worke, when <hi>providence</hi> offered the conveniency of a Celler to them, whereas they thought they muſt have digged a Vault by ſtrength of hand, to lay their Pouder in. How did God ſeeme to have caſt this <hi>Kingdome</hi> and <hi>Citty</hi> into a dead-ſleepe, that 36. <hi>barrells of gun-powder</hi> ſhould be conveyed into a Celler ſo neare the <hi>Parliament</hi>-Houſe, and a <hi>Parliament</hi> ſo neare and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112489:16"/>none have the leaſt ſuſpition of Treaſon. Could this have bin if <hi>God</hi> had not ſtupefied <hi>Men.</hi> God himſelfe ſeemed to take their part, and they who not many yeares before had <hi>ſworne God was turned Lutheran,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In 88.</note> began to hope, God was turned <hi>Catholick</hi> againe. God ſeemed to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired with them, and to ſay, <hi>They ſhall not know nor ſee.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the midſt of them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Till we are in the midſt of them. Joh. 20.19.</note> How? As <hi>Ieſus</hi> in the midſt of his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> ſaying, <hi>peace be unto you.</hi> No. But as the Enemies were in the midſt of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.<note place="margin">Pſal. 74.4.</note> 
               <hi>O GOD thy Enemies roare in the midſt of thy Congregation.</hi> They made account to have come <hi>into the midſt of them</hi> with ſuch roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as would have aſtoniſhed the Heavens, and made the Earth tremble. <hi>In the midſt of them,</hi> as the Daughter of <hi>Herodias</hi> was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Mat. 14.6.</note> only to ſuck bloud, <hi>to ſlay them,</hi> that is the end why they would be <hi>in the midct of them. And our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries ſaid, they ſhall not know nor ſee, till we are in the midſt of them and ſlay them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Slay them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Slay them.</note> Whom? <hi>The whole Aſsembly of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> and therein to <hi>quench</hi> the <hi>light,</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Nation.</hi> Never any Treaſon before this ſo <hi>deſtructive.</hi> Others were but <hi>petty</hi> Treaſons compared with this. <hi>This</hi> was the <hi>maſter-peice</hi> of all the <hi>pollicy</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Hell.</hi> Vnleſſe it were the <hi>Treaſon</hi> of <hi>Satan</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> to blow up all <hi>Man-kind</hi> in <hi>Adam, the repreſentative of it at once,</hi> no <hi>Treaſon</hi> like to this. This was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond unto that, of which they ſay, as he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of <hi>Goliahs ſword, None to that, None to that,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:112489:16"/>wherin the <hi>flowre of our Gentry,</hi> our whole <hi>Nobil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> the <hi>Princes of the bloud,</hi> the <hi>Lords annointed, the Royall ſeede</hi> were all devoted to one ſtroake of deſtruction. <hi>And our Adverſaries ſaid they ſhal not know nor ſee, til wee are in the midſt of them and ſlay them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Slay them.</hi> Aye ſuch Inſtruments of cruelty had they prepared for this <hi>ſlaughter,</hi> as no one of that Aſſembly could have fled from the <hi>fury</hi> of, had they the <hi>wings of Eagles,</hi> nor reſiſted the <hi>force</hi> of, had their <hi>fleſh</hi> bin as <hi>braſse,</hi> or their <hi>ſtrength</hi> as <hi>ſtones,</hi> or their <hi>bodies armed with the ſcales of</hi> the <hi>Leviathan.</hi> They were not <hi>Swords,</hi> nor <hi>Piſtols,</hi> nor <hi>poiſons,</hi> the <hi>ordinary weapons of</hi> Romes <hi>warre-fare,</hi> but Inſtruments more inevitably killing. 36. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rells of gun-powder,</hi> enough to have blowne to duſt, <hi>the ſtrongeſt Fort in Chriſtendome.</hi> Theſe were the <hi>Instruments of their cruelty,</hi> ſuch as were never found <hi>in the habitations of Simeon</hi> and <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi.</hi> With theſe they intended to come in <hi>the midſt of them and ſlay them.</hi> And that with ſuch <hi>a ſlaughter,</hi> as was never heard before. Shew me in any <hi>Hiſtory</hi> a preſident of the like ſlaughter as was intended here. Wicked <hi>Abimelech ſlew upon one ſtone threeſcore and tenne of</hi> Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deons <hi>ſonnes,</hi> yet <hi>one</hi> eſcaped: <hi>Ietham</hi> had his life ſaved. <hi>Bloudy Saul</hi> cauſed <hi>Fourſcore and five of the Priests of the Lord to be ſlayne in one day,</hi> yet <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Sonne of the high Prieſt had his <hi>life given him for a prey.</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious <hi>Athaliah</hi> ſought to deſtroy all the Kings ſeede, yet <hi>Ioaſh</hi> the Kings Sonne was <hi>preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. In the Maſsacre of</hi> France, above <hi>three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112489:17"/>thouſand ſlaine,</hi> yet <hi>ſome</hi> eſcaped even of thoſe that were appointed <hi>to the ſlaughter.</hi> But heere <hi>Oh mercileſse cruelty, not one man</hi> that had eſcaped, neither <hi>King,</hi> nor <hi>Prince,</hi> nor <hi>Lord,</hi> nor any of <hi>that Honourable Aſſembly,</hi> though all of them, as <hi>Zeba</hi> ſaid of <hi>the brethren of Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon,</hi> were men <hi>cach one reſembling the Sonne of a King,</hi> yet they had all <hi>periſhed together, in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not one eſcaping.</hi> The <hi>Devil</hi> dealt <hi>more mercifully</hi> then thus with <hi>Iob</hi> when hee ſlew his <hi>Sonnes</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> hee ſtill left one alive to carry the tydings, but heere all dye or none. And that in ſuch <hi>a crafty ſly way,</hi> as they ſhall never know who hurt them. <hi>They ſhal not know nor ſee.</hi> Nay the craft of our Adverſaries exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo farre, as to provide, not onely to hide themſelves from the ſight of them, whom they intended thus to cut off,<note place="margin">See a letter of M. <hi>W. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> to M. <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars</hi> before his Poëm on the 5. of <hi>Novem.</hi>
               </note> but from the reſt of the Nation. You know the wayes they had taken to caſt the <hi>Odium</hi> of that horrid Treaſon on the true Proteſtants, under the name of Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, if God had not in mercy delivered us from that conſpiracy, we had borne not onely the <hi>miſery,</hi> but the <hi>infamy</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">And cauſe the worke to ceaſe</note>
               <hi>And our Adverſaries ſaid, They ſhall not know nor ſee till wee are in the midſt of them, and ſlay them, and cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</hi> It is the worke they were about, that is the cauſe of all their rage and malice: They were about to make Lawes for ſetling true Religion, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing Popery. And as <hi>Pilat</hi> came upon the <hi>Galileans,</hi> when they were ſacrificing, and ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their bloud with their Sacrifices. And as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112489:17"/>the Adverſaries heare made account to come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and his builders, and temper their mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with their blouds, ſo did ours plot to come upon our <hi>Law makers,</hi> they <hi>ſhall write no Lawes, but in their owne blouds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Oh Lord, if this plot had taken, What a<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>That which P.</hi> Valderama <hi>fables con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning</hi> Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius <hi>his Lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, indeed would have bin true of theſe buil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ings.</hi> Cum pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>um propoſuit apud ſe militarem vitam abdicare, Do nus in quâ tum ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ota contren u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etes ejus concuſsa ſuerant, lig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a omnta &amp; trabes concre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uerunt Quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dum accidit cum in Mont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aliquo Sulp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u eo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>neum os a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eritur &amp; Flammae exinde erum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cipiunt, fic, <hi>&amp;c</hi> mille Terrores, mille Pavores, mille edium inceudia conſequu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erint. Nu us un qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Aetea out ign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us mons paria ſecit.</note> 
               <hi>Veſuvius,</hi> what an <hi>Etna</hi> had this place bin? What an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> what a <hi>Golgotha</hi> had this <hi>Land</hi> bin? What a <hi>Chaos</hi> had this <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> bin? how had our <hi>Lawes, Liberties, Religion</hi> bin ſwallowed up in that <hi>Fiery gulph,</hi> and <hi>buried in thoſe aſhes.</hi> How would that <hi>man of ſinne,</hi> that <hi>ſonne of perdition</hi> have ſatiated his thirſt of blood in the archivements of this Day, and have looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe <hi>piles of mangled, diſmembred bodies,</hi> and that horrid face of death, ſuch as was never ſeene before, with as much content as <hi>Haniball</hi> did upon a pit full of the bloud of Men, when he cryes out, <hi>O formoſum ſpectaculum.</hi> Or <hi>Valeſus</hi> the <hi>Aſian Proconſul,</hi> when trampling o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the carcaſſes of 300. Men whom hee had ſlaine, he cryed out <hi>O rem regiam.</hi> Or that Queene who when ſhee ſaw ſome of her Proteſtant ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects lying dead and ſtripped upon the Earth, cryed our. <hi>The goodlieſt tapeſtry that ever ſhee beheld.</hi> Many goodly bloudy ſights hath <hi>Antichrist</hi> glutted his cruell mind with. The Funerall piles of <hi>England</hi> in Queen <hi>Maries</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:112489:18"/>dayes. The <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> The <hi>warres</hi> of <hi>Germany.</hi> The <hi>butcheries</hi> of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Goodly <hi>ſights</hi> in the eyes of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> But to have ſeene a whole <hi>Parliament,</hi> and therein the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> of a whole <hi>Kingdome,</hi> blowne up in a moment! <hi>Thuarus</hi> writes that the Pope cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> to bee painted in his Pallace, ſurely had this Plot ſucceeded it ſhould have been<note n="*" place="margin">For though the plot ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not, yet <hi>F. Garnet</hi> had the honour to have his pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſet among the reit of <hi>Romes</hi> Saints, in the Ieſuites Church at <hi>Rome. Voluiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſat eſt.</hi> Gir. 1. Apol. <hi>contra</hi> Ieſuitas.</note> 
               <hi>portraied</hi> in his Holineſſe <hi>Chappell</hi> or <hi>Oratory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how came it to paſſe, that it ſucceeded not. Was there any thing wanting either in the wills or endeavours of our <hi>Adverſaries.</hi> No, <hi>our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries ſaid, They ſhall not know nor ſee, till wee are in the midſt of them and ſlay them.</hi> Nor did we till that <hi>very night,</hi> that <hi>Morning</hi> the <hi>fatall blow</hi> ſhould have been given. And then it was not any <hi>State vigilancy</hi> or <hi>prudence,</hi> but <hi>meerely divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> that brought to <hi>light</hi> this worke of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The particular acts of which providence, I need not inſtance, you know the Story, and all that know it will acknowledge, <hi>That if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the arme of GOD were revealed in any deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, it was in this;</hi> onely that by all which hath beene ſpoken, our hearts may bee raiſed to the higher ſtraine of thankfullneſſe, Let me as I have ſet before you the ſubtilty and cruelty of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries in the <hi>invention</hi> of this Treaſon, preſent unto you the mercy of God in the <hi>prevention</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>O how <hi>freely</hi> did God deliver us from the bloudy <hi>intendment</hi> of our <hi>Adverſaries. Many</hi> Deliverances hath God wrought for our <hi>Selves,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:112489:18"/>for other <hi>Churches,</hi> for his <hi>Church</hi> in former times, but was there ever any ſo free as this?<note place="margin">Eſth. 4.16.</note> God delivered his <hi>Church, from the bloudy conſpiracie of</hi> Haman. A worke of aſtoniſhing power and mercy. But what Prayers, what Teares, what Faſtings and Wreſtlings did it coſt <hi>Eſther</hi> and <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and the whole Church, ere they could obtaine that Deliverance? It was a gracious Deliverance, GOD wrought for his Infantile Church, in reſcuing <hi>Peter</hi> from the hands of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> but it was wrought by aboundant importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>unceſſant Prayer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 12.5.</note> 
               <hi>Prayer was made without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Church unto GOD for him.</hi> But this Deliverance came not upon the <hi>wings of our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> but Gods free mercy, wee <hi>knew not our danger,</hi> and therefore could not make <hi>Deliverance</hi> the ſubject of our <hi>Prayers. Maſſes</hi> were ſaid in <hi>Rome,</hi> for the good ſucceſſe of the Catholicke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, but no <hi>Prayers</hi> in <hi>England</hi> for our <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> from <hi>their Treaſon,</hi> and yet wee delivered, <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Mercy! A people to be delivered by their God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſeeke Deliverance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And delivered <hi>ſo fully.</hi> You know the <hi>Plot</hi> was laid for a <hi>full deſtruction,</hi> to cut off every Perſon in that Honourable Aſſembly: to <hi>blow</hi> them all up, teare them all in peeces, and in and with them the whole Nation. But ſee how <hi>fully</hi> God prevented their miſchievous deſigne. That not a limbe of <hi>any one</hi> of them was ſhaken, not <hi>one bone broken.</hi> The <hi>Deliverance</hi> was like that of the three <hi>Children</hi> in the fiery fornace. <hi>There was not ſo much as a haire of their head ſindged, neither did the fire ſo much as take hold upon any of their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112489:19"/>Garments, neither was there ſo much as the ſent thereof upon them.</hi> Like that of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> from the fury of <hi>Senacherib,</hi> who comming up againſt the Church full of pride and rage, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding nothing, but to <hi>breake in peeces and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy:</hi> ſaith GOD, <hi>He ſhall not come up againſt this City, nor ſhoot an arrow there.</hi> So ſaid the LORD to our <hi>Adverſaries.</hi> You <hi>ſhall not come up againſt this Aſſembly, nor fire one corne of Powder,</hi> nor <hi>ſhed one droppe of bloud there, where they intended to have filled all with bloud and fire, O admirable Deliverance:</hi> Hath GOD delivered <hi>Germany</hi> thus. Is <hi>Ireland</hi> thus delivered, O <hi>England, England!</hi> The <hi>aſhes</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> The <hi>bloud</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> proclaime thy Deliverance this day, glorious in the fulneſſe of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And not onely in the <hi>fulneſse</hi> of our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but in the <hi>confuſion of our enemies,</hi> whom God tooke this day in their owne <hi>Pits</hi> and <hi>ſnares.</hi> And the plot they had laid to blow us up, did recoyle and blow up themſelves. God turned it to their owne deſtruction. That which they had deſigned for the advantage of their <hi>Catholike</hi> cauſe and Religion (a good cauſe and a good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that muſt bee advanced by ſuch ſinfull, devilliſh wayes) hath been the greateſt diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to their cauſe: All the ſtreames of <hi>Tyber</hi> will never waſh off that blot of juſt infamy which this Treaſon hath faſtned on them, till <hi>Babylon ſinke like a Mil ſtone into the bottome of the Sea,</hi> it will never be waſhed off, <hi>This was the Lords do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:</hi> This turning the Wheele upon our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, this bringing their miſchiefe upon their own
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112489:19"/>heads, it was the <hi>Lords doings, and it is marvellous in our eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now as that great King, <hi>Eſther</hi> 7. <hi>When he read in the records of the</hi> Chronicles, <hi>that</hi> Morde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cai <hi>had diſcovered a Treaſon againſt the King,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently enquired, <hi>What honour and dignity had been done to</hi> Mordecai <hi>for this.</hi> So do you. You have ſeene this day a briefe record of that which deſerves a larger Chronicle. You have ſeene how the God of Heaven prevented and diſappointed a Treaſon as darke and cruell as Hell, intended againſt the whole State and Kingdome. Now your parts it is <hi>(Honourable and Beloved)</hi> who repreſentative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are the whole Nation, your parts it is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, what <hi>honour, what dignity hath been done to God for this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True it is the Parliament then aſſembled, whoſe the Deliverance more immediately was, did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine this <hi>Anniverſary,</hi> which wee celebrate this Day. But beſides this, what honour, what dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity hath been done to God. What hath been done for the advancement of his Glory, the propagation of his Goſpell, the repreſſing of Popery from that Deliverance unto this Day. Doe you in your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences thinke, that the bare keeping this deliverance inmemory, or an acknowledging of it in our aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, as at this day, is ſufficient retribution of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and honour to our great deliverer. Did not <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> doe as much as this; did not hee indite a Song in the praiſe of that God, that had delivered him from the ſentence of death. You have it <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38. to. yet is it not ſaid, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.25. <hi>But</hi> Hezekiah <hi>retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not unto the LORD, according to the benefit
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112489:20"/>done unto him. Hezekiah</hi> returned <hi>praiſe</hi> unto the Lord, even a <hi>Pſalme</hi> of praiſe. But <hi>Hezekiah</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned not unto the Lord, according to the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit done unto him: Therefore was wrath <hi>upon him and upon</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Ieruſalem. May it not be ſaid ſo of <hi>England</hi> for all our <hi>Anniverſaries,</hi> our <hi>Sermons</hi> and <hi>Songs</hi> of <hi>praiſe,</hi> But <hi>England</hi> hath not <hi>returned</hi> unto the Lord, <hi>according to the benefits done unto them. Quid verba andiam, facta cum videam.</hi> Care I, ſaith <hi>God,</hi> for the flattering <hi>praiſes</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> when I <hi>ſee</hi> the curſed <hi>practiſes</hi> of <hi>England!</hi> Have not my <hi>purest Truthes</hi> been adulterated in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Romes</hi> groſſeſt errours entertained in <hi>England,</hi> and that even ſince <hi>this Deliverance?</hi> Have not my <hi>pureſt Ordinances</hi> beene polluted in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Romes</hi> groſſeſt ſuperſtitions pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in <hi>England?</hi> Have not <hi>Maſſes</hi> beene o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly celebrated with a <hi>greater confluence</hi> of <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes</hi> to them, then to <hi>Sermons</hi> and <hi>Sacraments?</hi> Have they not publiſhed <hi>edictes</hi> againſt the <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of my Day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.6.</note> but none againſt the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the <hi>Maſſe?</hi> Have they not <hi>without Law, againſt Law</hi> perſecuted my <hi>Miniſters,</hi> my <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> impriſoning them, compelling them to vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary <hi>exile,</hi> while they have neglected to put in <hi>execution</hi> their owne <hi>Lawes againſt</hi> Romiſh Prieſts and Ieſuites<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Doe you thus requite the Lord, O fooliſh Nation and unwiſe?</hi> Did I deliver you this Day from <hi>Romiſh</hi> cruelties, that you ſhould deliver up your ſelves to <hi>Romiſh</hi> Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Idolatry? Is this to returne to the LORD, <hi>according to the benefits hee hath done?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:112489:20"/>
            <p>Ariſe, ariſe yee <hi>Princes of the tribes of England,</hi> yee members of the <hi>honour able houſes of Parliament act</hi> ſomething this day, <hi>worthy</hi> of <hi>your ſelves, worthy</hi> of this <hi>day, worthy</hi> of this <hi>deliverance, worthy</hi> of your <hi>great deliverer.</hi> God (I perſwade my ſelf) hath reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved unto <hi>you</hi> the glory of <hi>returning unto him according to this dayes mercy.</hi> You have begun to do <hi>more</hi> for the <hi>repreſsing</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> for the <hi>reforming</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>doctrine, worſhip, diſcipline,</hi> then your <hi>forefathers</hi> have done ever ſince the <hi>firſt hand</hi> was put to the work of <hi>reformation. Go on</hi> in the <hi>name of the Lord,</hi> in the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>his might,</hi> in the <hi>multitudes</hi> of <hi>his ſtrength:</hi> Go on to root out, not only <hi>Popery</hi> but <hi>all</hi> that is <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh.</hi> Let <hi>this day</hi> adde ſomething towards the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of that work. <hi>Some ſuch thing</hi> I ſuppoſe was in the hearts of the <hi>honourable Houſes</hi> when they made choice of <hi>this particular day</hi> for the <hi>aſſembly of Divines</hi> to meet on. Why to meet this day, if not to <hi>deliberate</hi> and <hi>adviſe</hi> ſomething that might tend to the <hi>farther honour</hi> of the <hi>Authour</hi> of this <hi>dayes deliverance</hi> and the <hi>farther confuſion</hi> of the <hi>Authour</hi> of this <hi>dayes trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the Romiſh Religion?</hi> Wel, that <hi>aſſembly</hi> by the ſaid diſtempers of theſe bleeding times is yet <hi>ſuſpended.</hi> I beſeech you make this the work of yours: and when you returne to your <hi>Parliament Houſe</hi> again let the <hi>firſt queſtion</hi> put to <hi>vote</hi> this day be <hi>Davids Quid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribuam?</hi> pſalm. 116. <hi>What ſhall I render to the Lord for all his benefits towards me?</hi> Let this be the queſtion, and the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>wiſdome</hi> and <hi>grace</hi> direct you in your <hi>Reſolves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what ever <hi>God</hi> ſhall reveale to make <hi>most for his glory,</hi> his <hi>Churches peace</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> the <hi>union</hi> of the <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> the <hi>extirpation</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> let that be the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112489:21"/>
               <hi>Crowning Act</hi> of this day. <hi>Scripio Africanus</hi> being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed before the <hi>Tribunes of the people</hi> and the day of his triall falling upon the ſame moneth and day in which be had ſome yeares before wonne a great vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory over <hi>Hanniball in Affrick.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iiv</hi> 8. <hi>c</hi> 40.</note> Vpon his firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance addreſſes himſelf to the people in this wiſe. <hi>Hoc die,</hi> Quirites, <hi>cum</hi> Annibale <hi>faeliciter pugnatum eſt &amp;c. This day</hi> Gentlemen <hi>did I fight with</hi> Hanniball <hi>in</hi> Affrick <hi>with good ſucceſſe: therefore leaving Law ſuites I paſſe directly to the</hi> Capitoll <hi>to ſalute the</hi> Gods <hi>and give them thankes.</hi> Hoc <hi>die</hi> Quirites. <hi>This day,</hi> Knightes <hi>and</hi> Gentlemen, <hi>God himſelf fought for you againſt Rome,</hi> ô do not think it enough that you have come to ſalute <hi>God</hi> in his <hi>Temple</hi> this morning and give him praiſe; but when you returne to your <hi>Parliament-Houſe</hi> againe letting all other buſineſſes ſleep a while, in the <hi>firſt place Reſolve</hi> this queſtion <hi>Quid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribuam?</hi> What ſhall I render to the Lord for all his benefits?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Application ſecond by way of Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>And this I would the rather excite you to (<hi>Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and beloved in our Lord</hi> becauſe, <hi>due thankfulneſſe for former deliverances is a happie meanes to procure new.</hi> God is <hi>never weary of delivering a people that ſtudyes thankfulneſſe.</hi> And hath not <hi>England,</hi> hath not the <hi>Parliament</hi> need of the arme of God to be ſtretched out againe for their deliverance. For have we now no <hi>adverſaries?</hi> or have <hi>our adverſaries</hi> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their <hi>natures,</hi> put of their wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed <hi>craft</hi> and <hi>cruelty</hi> forgott their ould <hi>note</hi> to <hi>ſay, They ſhall not know nor ſee till we are in the middest of them and ſlay them and cauſe the work to ceaſe?</hi> No certainely. Sooner ſhall the <hi>Leopard change his ſports or the Ethiopian his skin</hi> then <hi>our adverſaries</hi> change their <hi>ſcrafty bloudy diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:112489:21"/>or ceaſe to plot ruine againſt us, till they have utterly ruined themſelves by their owne plots. Have <hi>our adverſaries</hi> thinke you bin ſleeping ever ſince this powder treaſon? <hi>You</hi> that have bin now theſe two yeares wraſtling with them, you know what their Molitions have bin and in your ſeverall <hi>Remonſtrances</hi> have made them known: yet give me leave to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the reſt of our brethren a little of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our adverſaries</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> have bin plotting their preſent rebellion theſe <hi>ſeaventeen yeares</hi> as ſome have depoſed.<note place="margin">See the <hi>Fri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh</hi> Remonſtrance</note> Theſe <hi>ſeaventeen yeares</hi> they have bin mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>fireworks</hi> and laying <hi>traines</hi> for the <hi>kindling</hi> of that <hi>combuſtion</hi> which now devoures that <hi>miſerable Kingdome.</hi> And what have our adverſaries bin doing here the meane while, Think you, nothing? Whence then proceeded thoſe long <hi>intermiſsions</hi> of <hi>Parliaments</hi> that we began to feare our <hi>Parliaments</hi> would prove like thoſe <hi>Roman ſolemnities:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ludi ſeculares. Alexan. Gen. Dier. li. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>18</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quos nemo mortalium vidit unquam nec viſurus eſt.</hi> Which no man <hi>lived to ſee twice being held but once in a hundred yeares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence came the immature <hi>diſſolutions</hi> of ſo many <hi>Parliaments?</hi> but from the plots of theſe <hi>our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries?</hi> He that knowes not where the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> lies, may learn of <hi>Englands enemies.</hi> For as the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> when they knew that <hi>Samſons ſtrength</hi> lay in his <hi>haire</hi> plotted to cut off that and then they ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily <hi>bound him, put out his eyes</hi> and made him <hi>grinde in their mill.</hi> So <hi>our adverſaries</hi> knowing our <hi>ſtrength</hi> to lye in <hi>our Parliaments</hi> have bin <hi>ever plotting</hi> to cut off them. <hi>One Parliament</hi> they attempted <hi>to blow up with powder</hi> but <hi>many a Parliament</hi> they <hi>have blown up without powder</hi> that ſo our <hi>Parliaments</hi> being <hi>intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, interrupted</hi> they might at once lay <hi>bandes upon us,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:112489:22"/>and put <hi>out our eyes</hi> that we ſhould not <hi>ſee</hi> our owne bondage, <hi>lay us</hi> in our Lawes <hi>and</hi> liberties <hi>and we ſhould neither know nor ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſth.</hi> 7.4.</note> And if <hi>only</hi> in <hi>our Lawes and liberties,</hi> If as <hi>Eſther</hi> ſaid, <hi>We had only bin ſold for bondmen and bondwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> the miſcheif had bin more tollerable. But had not <hi>our adverſaries</hi> plotred to <hi>ſlay us</hi> as the <hi>two wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes were ſlaine in the Revelation? To ſlay us</hi> by taking the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>life</hi> from us? Did they not <hi>ſay, we will come upon them and they ſhall neither know nor ſee tell we are in the middeſt of them and cauſe that work to ceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know there are many in the Nation (and may be ſome here) that cannot yet be perſwaded there was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any deſign for the <hi>alteration of Religion</hi> amongſt us. Such I beſeech in the <hi>ſpirit of meekneſſe</hi> to lend me a <hi>patient</hi> and <hi>unprejudiced</hi> eare. I ſtand not hear to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime againſt any <hi>perſons</hi> or <hi>rankes of men:</hi> but to ſpeak the <hi>words of truth and ſoberneſſe.</hi> I know that I ſtand this day <hi>not only before a great Court</hi> but before <hi>a greater God</hi> to whom I muſt give account for what I now ſpeak.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contzen. Politic. li.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. Layes a plott for the alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: which is Laid downe in certaine rules.</note> 
               <hi>Adam Contzen,</hi> A Jeſuite of <hi>Mentz</hi> in his <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond booke of Politickes</hi> the Eighteenth <hi>Chapter,</hi> hath drawne a plot for the <hi>cheating</hi> of a people of the <hi>true Religion</hi> by ſleight <hi>of hand</hi> and the <hi>ſerving in</hi> of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery againe upon them <hi>by art of legerdemaine,</hi> that they <hi>ſhall neither know nor ſee.</hi> The method of this (which certainely is one of Satans <hi>Methods</hi>) he layes downe in certaine rules. Be pleaſed but to obſerve how <hi>exactly</hi> the <hi>late times</hi> have moved <hi>according to thoſe Rules</hi> and then judge of their deſignes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">His firſt rule.</note> His firſt rule is this. To <hi>proceed</hi> as <hi>Muſicians doe in tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112489:22"/>their inſtruments:</hi> Who <hi>ſtraine their ſtrings with agentle hand</hi> and <hi>ſet them up by little and little. Or as</hi> Phyſitians <hi>doe in curing diſeaſes who abate noxious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors by degrees and pauſes.</hi> This rule was obſerved both for the <hi>deſtructive</hi> and <hi>adſtructive</hi> way. For the <hi>deſtruction of the true Religion,</hi> and the advancing of the falſe they had learned this wiſdome to proceed by <hi>degrees</hi> and <hi>pauſes.</hi> And <hi>first</hi> for the <hi>deſtruction of the true Religion.</hi> To <hi>ſuſpend all</hi> the <hi>Orthodoxe prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> in the land <hi>at once</hi> would have made too <hi>great a noiſe</hi> therefore proceed <hi>by degrees.</hi> And firſt ſuſpend <hi>all Lecturers</hi> which will not <hi>constantly</hi> practiſe the <hi>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</hi> Then after a little pauſe, Clap downe <hi>all Lecturers</hi> as an order of <hi>Vagrants</hi> not to be toller ated in the <hi>Church.</hi> When that is done: Forbid all <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors</hi> and <hi>Incumbents</hi> preaching in their owne <hi>pariſh Churches</hi> upon <hi>weeke dayes.</hi> Next inhibit <hi>preaching</hi> upon the <hi>Lords Day in the After noone</hi> under pretence of advancing <hi>Catechiſing</hi> by that meanes: and yet with in a little while after <hi>forbidding all Catecheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call expoſition,</hi> tying men to the <hi>bare words</hi> of the <hi>Primmer Catechiſine:</hi> As <hi>ſoone after</hi> they forbad all <hi>praying</hi> but in the <hi>words of the Canon.</hi> Now what can any ingenuous man thinke the deſigne of all this was; But to rob us of <hi>preaching and praying,</hi> and thereby of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> and <hi>true Religion</hi> wholly in <hi>concluſion?</hi> Only to doe it by <hi>degrees</hi> for feare of <hi>noiſe</hi> and <hi>tumult,</hi> to doe it ſo <hi>as we ſhould neither know nor ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the <hi>adſtructive</hi> way. The <hi>rebuilding of Rome</hi> among us did they not proceed by the <hi>me ſteppes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Urging the conſtant and <hi>full practiſe</hi> of the old <hi>Ceremonies</hi> beyond the intention either of <hi>Law</hi> of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:112489:23"/>or <hi>Canon.</hi> Then <hi>bringing</hi> in an <hi>Idolatrous fardell</hi> of new <hi>pop ſhiſuperſtitions</hi> without warrant either of <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Canon</hi> but their owne <hi>paper injunctions; forcing</hi> their obſervance upon <hi>Ministers</hi> and <hi>people:</hi> but by pauſes and degrees.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> the <hi>Table</hi> muſt be <hi>railed in;</hi> ſoone after ſet in an <hi>Altar poſture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then thirdly, <hi>All</hi> muſt be compelled to <hi>come</hi> and <hi>kneele</hi> before it or not <hi>receave the Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then it muſt <hi>becried</hi> up as the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum;</hi> the place of <hi>Gods chiefe reſidence upon earth;</hi> the <hi>Seate</hi> and <hi>Throne of God Almighty.</hi> And there up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Fifthly, All mens <hi>faces in prayer</hi> muſt be turned towards that. Men <hi>may,</hi> yea <hi>muſt ſay ſome,</hi> adore and bow before it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What <hi>could the intent of all this be?</hi> but after the <hi>Altar</hi> to bring in the <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> and with their <hi>wooden worſhip</hi> the <hi>breaden God.</hi> Only to doe it by <hi>degrees</hi> that wee ſhould not know nor ſee. So in doctrine. <hi>Firſt,</hi> bring in <hi>Arminian doctrines,</hi> then the <hi>popiſh</hi> will eaſily follow. Let the <hi>Serpent</hi> but <hi>winde in his head,</hi> he will ſoone <hi>worke</hi> in his <hi>whole body.</hi> Let <hi>Arminia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſine</hi> but obtaine <hi>countenance</hi> and <hi>licence</hi> in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; Our <hi>Pulpits, Schooles, Preſſes,</hi> will ſoone bee filled with popiſh <hi>doctrins:</hi> witneſſe the publiſhing of ſo many points of popery one after another, <hi>ſpecially thoſe two.</hi> That the <hi>Pope is not Antichriſt.</hi> And that the Church of <hi>Rome is a true viſible Church. Alta ſic ſurgunt maenia Romoa.</hi> Thus (according to the rule of their <hi>Maſter Ieſuite</hi>) they ſeeke <hi>to re establiſh Rome by degrees. They ſaid, they ſhall not know nor ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">His ſecond Rule.</note> His ſecond <hi>Rule</hi> is this. <hi>To preſse the examples and practiſes of ſome as a good means to draw on the reſt.</hi> And
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:112489:23"/>was not this familiar with them? to dazle the <hi>eyes</hi> of the meaner and <hi>leſſe judicious people</hi> of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, with the <hi>practices</hi> of great <hi>perſons.</hi> If any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to <hi>tartle</hi> or be troubled at the matter what was their preſent anſwer? <hi>My Lord Biſhop</hi> doth thus and thus: and <hi>my Lords Grace of Canterbury</hi> doth thus and thus. <hi>The Knights</hi> of the <hi>most noble order of the Garter bow.</hi> Verſus Altare,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A C.</hi> Speech in the Starre-Chamber, <hi>p</hi> 47</note> 
               <hi>towards the Altar at their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtallement,</hi> His <hi>Majesties Chappell</hi> is thus and thus adorned. By theſe &amp; the like pretences <hi>caſting a miſt</hi> before the peoples eyes that <hi>ſome did not,</hi> others <hi>durſt not</hi> ſee any thing tending towards the altering of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. <hi>Our adverſaries ſaid they ſhall neither know nor ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">His third Rule.</note> His third Rule is this. <hi>That arch Heretickes and ſuch as are teachers of Hereſie must be baniſhed the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, at once if it may ſafely bee done, but if not by degrees.</hi> It is eaſie to know who are the <hi>Ieſuites, Arch-Heretickes,</hi> the moſt <hi>active, orthodoxe</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. For the rooting out of ſuch the <hi>Ieſuite</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes a method of twelve or thirteene ſteppes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cout. Pol. lib.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 18. <hi>§.</hi> 6.</note> For which (though well worth the relating) <hi>I</hi> referre you to his book, leaſt this diſcourſe ſhould ſwell to much. Only in ſumme. Let me ſhew you how their <hi>operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> hath beene according to this <hi>Rule.</hi> The <hi>Arch-Heretickes</hi> and Teachers of hereſie in <hi>England</hi> have beene counted the <hi>Puritan Preachers,</hi> though they <hi>teach nothing</hi> but <hi>conſonant to Scripture</hi> and the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>Doctrine of the Church,</hi> yet they are the <hi>teachers of hereſie:</hi> and being <hi>too many</hi> to root out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>once,</hi> it muſt be <hi>done by degrees,</hi> that it may effected with <hi>more eaſe</hi> and <hi>leſſe noiſe,</hi> and therefore,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> eaſt <hi>all</hi> thoſe out <hi>of the miniſtery,</hi> that will
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:112489:24"/>not be <hi>punctuall</hi> and <hi>full conformiſts</hi> to the <hi>old Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</hi> Next (becauſe there were a company <hi>of conformable Puritans</hi> as themſelves ſtiled them) they procure <hi>an edict for recreations</hi> upon the <hi>Lords Day and</hi> this muſt be <hi>publiſhed by Miniſters:</hi> that ſuch as could ſtand under <hi>the ceremonies</hi> (though groaning for the burden) might <hi>fall and be broken in pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ces under this.</hi> And yet becauſe ſome men <hi>ſuſpected</hi> of <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſme</hi> might have a <hi>latitude</hi> here bey ond their <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren;</hi> They have a <hi>third</hi> engine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd that is <hi>injoyning new Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>adorations,</hi> that if any could <hi>ſwallow the book</hi> yet they might diſcover &amp; caſt them out by <hi>ſtraining here.</hi> To this they adde <hi>a fourth. Prayers</hi> and <hi>Proclamations</hi> to be read againſt our <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Scotts.</hi> And their <hi>laſt</hi> and <hi>greateſt</hi> engine which was like the <hi>powder plot</hi> againſt the <hi>godly mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi> of the nation <hi>to blow up the reliques of them at once</hi> was the <hi>oath for Epiſcopacie.</hi> By theſe <hi>ſucceſsive ſtratagems</hi> they made account utterly to extirpate thoſe <hi>Arch-Hereticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it was ſomtimes ſaid to <hi>Elijah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Him that eſcapeth the ſword of</hi> Hazael, <hi>ſhall</hi> Iehu <hi>ſlay-and him that eſcapeth the ſword of</hi> Iehu <hi>ſhall</hi> Eliſha <hi>ſlay.</hi> So had they ſaid. <hi>Him</hi> that eſcapeth the dint of the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> ſhal the <hi>book of ſports</hi> ſlay, and him that eſcapeth the book of <hi>ſports</hi> ſhall the <hi>new injunctions ſlay:</hi> and <hi>him</hi> that eſcapeth the <hi>new injunctions</hi> ſhall the <hi>proclamations ſlay,</hi> and <hi>him</hi> that eſcapeth the <hi>proclamations,</hi> ſhal the <hi>oath ſlay.</hi> And this by <hi>degrees</hi> and <hi>pauſes</hi> that they <hi>ſhall neither know nor ſee till we ſlay them and cauſe the work to ceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">His fourth Rule.</note> The fourth rule is this. <hi>That thoſe which are adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries to the true Religion (which with him is Popery) be put by their dignities, places &amp; offices.</hi> I think none here
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:112489:24"/>is ſuch a ſtranger in <hi>England</hi> but from his own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg can wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſſe this. The <hi>beſtowing</hi> of <hi>all offices,</hi> the <hi>collating</hi> of <hi>benefices,</hi> the <hi>election</hi> of <hi>Maſters,</hi> and <hi>fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes</hi> of <hi>Colledges</hi> in both <hi>Vniverſities,</hi> who had the over-ruling hand in them all, <hi>the power of mandamus,</hi> but <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>his faction?</hi> And <hi>whom</hi> were they <hi>conferred</hi> upon <hi>Vſually?</hi> Men <hi>infamous</hi> for and<note n="a" place="margin">So Leontius Biſhop of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch a diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Arrian was obſerved to diſreſpect all Orthodox men and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr no one in the Church but ſuch as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianiſme: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. Theod. 2 24. Quis enim non facilè Pruita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos in Anglia redig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in Or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inem ſi E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or m approbatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ab tis ex. torqueat, Contz vbiſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra paragrap. 9</note> 
               <hi>impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> in <hi>Arminian</hi> and <hi>Popiſh</hi> opinions. <hi>Proteſted Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minianiſme</hi> and <hi>bold faced Popery</hi> the only <hi>ſpeedy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring way</hi> to Church preferment.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> His fifth rule is. <hi>To make the Proteſtant Religion odious, by laying load upon ſuch tenents as are moſt ſubject to harſheſt conſtructions.</hi> In this <hi>our adverſaries</hi> have not bin ſparing. <hi>Quot plaustra convitiorum</hi> have they poured out upon ſome <hi>doctrines</hi> of <hi>our Religion</hi> ſpecialy the <hi>points of grace?</hi> The pulpits <hi>of Italy</hi> and <hi>Rome never ſpitt more gall</hi> and <hi>venome</hi> againſt the <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines</hi> of <hi>Election, free grace, juſtification by faith, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance, &amp;c.</hi> nor never <hi>ſweat</hi> more to <hi>exaggerate</hi> the <hi>ſeeming abſurdities,</hi> which <hi>carnall men</hi> would <hi>draw from them</hi> then ſome of ours have done.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> His ſixth rule is. <hi>To foment the quarells that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Proteſtants and ſtrengthen that party that is neareſt compliance with Rome.</hi> And here, the wretch hath the <hi>unhappines</hi> to <hi>preſcribe one thing as the proper meanes of Englands cure. For who (ſaith he) might not eaſily reduce the Puritans of England into order</hi> (you know what the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> reducing into order is) <hi>if he could extort from them an approbation of the Biſhops?</hi> And had they not attempted and almoſt effected this? They had made us <hi>their ſlaves</hi> before and <hi>were they not about to make us ſwear we would be ſo for ever?</hi> Certainly though nothing but <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> floated in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112489:25"/>the <hi>ſurface of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath,</hi> yet <hi>Popery</hi> was in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the &amp;c.</hi> of it o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>reducing the Puritans of England into order, ſenſu Pontificio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">His ſeventh rule.</note> His ſeventh is this. <hi>That all private Conventiles and publick meetings muſt be forbidden.</hi> For <hi>private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles</hi> you all know, that to meet together <hi>to pray</hi> or <hi>to conferre</hi> (which with them was a <hi>Conventicle</hi>) was <hi>Peccatum irremiſsible.</hi> A man might at a better rate almoſt anſwer any thing then <hi>ſuch a meeting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>publick meetings.</hi> The ancient laudable exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of prophecying (I mean not in that ſence the word is lately taken for private ſpirits to interpret Scripture, but prophecying by men in office peculiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gifted and called to that work) <hi>theſe are baniſhed.</hi> The <hi>publick</hi> and moſt <hi>frequentod lectures blasted. Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick fastes</hi> by conſent of <hi>Miniſters</hi> (which had of long time bin uſed in many parts of the Kingdome) were become <hi>piacular.</hi> A <hi>ſermon</hi> at next Church, the <hi>forbidden fruit,</hi> when they had none at home or worſe then non. <hi>Our adverſaries</hi> have bin but too diligent to <hi>ſuppreſſ not only private Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venticles but publick Aſſembl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">His eighth rule.</note> The eighth meanes is. <hi>By ſeverity of Lawes and puniſhments to compell the obstinate unto duty and yet the rigour of the Law muſt be ſlowly drawn out and not against all, but only ſuch as be moſt dangerous.</hi> Now what ſeverity, not only <hi>Ad ſummum jus</hi> to the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gheſt <hi>apex</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> but even <hi>Supra jus</hi> beyond the <hi>extent</hi> and <hi>rigour of the Law,</hi> hath bin uſed <hi>to ſuch</hi> as <hi>stood in the way</hi> of their <hi>great deſigne,</hi> let the <hi>walles of their high Commiſsion ſpeak.</hi> Our <hi>Chronicles</hi> report, That when our forefathers demolliſhed the <hi>Abbies</hi> they found in their <hi>walles</hi> and <hi>vaultes</hi> and <hi>pondes</hi> heapes of <hi>ſculles</hi> and <hi>bones,</hi> the monuments of their
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:112489:25"/>Smoothered <hi>crueltyes.</hi> I doubt not but the <hi>aboliſhers of that high Commiſsion</hi> have found as manifeſt evidence of their <hi>cruell practiſes: heapes</hi> of the <hi>bloud of innocents,</hi> whoſe <hi>skin hath bin flead from of them and their bones broken and they and their families chopped in pieces as fleſh for the cauldron.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah.</hi> 3.</note> And this fruit they reaped of their ſeverity managed with this art which the <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit</hi> promiſed.<note place="margin">Ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio quae prove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctos non ad ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat, aetatem ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men puenlem Catholicam reddet.</note> That though compulſory Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could do no good upon old ſtanders yet it would render the younger ſort Catholicks.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">His ninth rule.</note> The ninth meanes and (as he ſaith) of <hi>all the reſt most effectuall is. That ſuch as are in authority do religiouſly practiſe and maintaine integrity of life and purity of manners.</hi> The <hi>reformation of Religion</hi> (that is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing of <hi>Popery</hi> into a <hi>reformed Church</hi>) <hi>will go on very ſlowly and prove very difficult unleſſe the Prelats and Doctors ſhall outſhine the whole Common wealth not only in innocency but in reputation and fame of inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And certainly this rule they had conned (ſome of them) <hi>Ad amuſsim</hi> or elſe they could never have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſo farre upon the <hi>heart</hi> of <hi>our Soveraign</hi> as to leave the diſpoſing of all <hi>Church affaires</hi> wholly <hi>unto them.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Arts of Diſſembling Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes have for the moſt part been Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently skilled in &amp; Sometimes a good Prince hath been overreached by it. Quem ubi vident conſtanter Religioni adhaerentem non adeò temerari ſunt, ut directè calu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nientur &amp; traducant apud cum Orthodoxam Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem: ſed occaſiones commodas accipiunt, quibus deplorent turbatam pacem Eceleſiae, hortantur Prineipem ad eam reſtituendam, id facilè eſſe dicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, auferatur modo Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis ſtudium: quod diſſidium non ſit in rebus Magni Monumenti, ſed exigui Pondexis &amp;c. Vedell. de Prud. vet. Eccleſ. l. 2. c. 5. See the Ep. Ded. of the relation of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between a Ieſuit &amp; W. L. fol. penult.</note> If they had not in his eye, demeaned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as the only <hi>Saints upon earth,</hi> as <hi>incarnate An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, men</hi> wholly <hi>compoſed</hi> of <hi>devotion to God, compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to his Church, greif for the rents and breaches of it, zeale for the peace and good of it:</hi> what but this ſhould
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:112489:26"/>prevaile with our ſoveraign to abandon this Church into the hands of that faction, I know not. But un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly it ſtands not with reaſon. That a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Prince</hi> ſhould <hi>knowingly and willingly</hi> give way to the re-eſtabliſhing of the <hi>Popiſh Religion</hi> &amp; therein <hi>Ipſo facto,</hi> diveſt himſelf of <hi>his ſupremacy</hi> and lay <hi>his head</hi> at the <hi>Popes feet</hi> for <hi>him</hi> to <hi>kick</hi> of the <hi>Crown</hi> from <hi>his Royall brow</hi> with a <hi>ſpurne of his diſdainfull foot</hi> at pleaſure. But why the Biſhops (ſpecially ſuch of them have bin obſerved to wiſh well to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery <hi>Abincunabulis</hi>) ſhould contrive and carry on ſuch a plot ſome reaſon may appeare. For could th y once have obtained this; <hi>That Popery ſhould have triumphed</hi> over the <hi>reformed Religion.</hi> The <hi>Miter</hi> would ſoon have trampled upon the Crown. <hi>Haec enim eſt veritas,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bellarm.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Haerc enim eſt v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tas quicquid i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuxe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>o, Epiſcop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s eſt Pater &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor &amp; Docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam Princip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s quam reliqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> populi. Et ſe, cundum haec Nom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>PRINCEPS, SVBDITVS</hi> eſſe <hi>DEBET</hi> ſuo <hi>EPISCO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PO</hi> &amp; <hi>NON EPISCOPVS PRINCIPI:</hi> Bellarm, de of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio Principis Chriſt. l. 1. c 5.</note> 
               <hi>This is the truth what ever cuſtome hath introduced that the</hi> Biſhop <hi>is the father and paſtor and Doctor as well of the</hi> Prince <hi>as of the reſt of the</hi> people. <hi>And according unto theſe appellations</hi> the Prince ought to be <hi>ſubject</hi> to his Biſhop <hi>and not the</hi> Biſhop <hi>to his</hi> Prince. <hi>Vnuſquiſque</hi> ſaith<note n="b" place="margin">Vnuſqu ſque Rex ſubditus eſt ſuo Epiſcopo in Soiritualibus niſa à Pontifice exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur. Suarez defenſ. fid. l. 3. cap. 17. ſec. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Suarez. Every King is ſubject to his Biſhop in ſpiritualibus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he be exempted by the Pope.</hi> A brave world this had bin for the Prelacy and the whole Clergy too. To have <hi>bin exempted from the power of Lawes and civilly dicature.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Leges non obligant Clenicos ex vi Iuriſdictionis Laicae nec <hi>POSS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NT</hi> Reges obligare Clericos Legibus illis peculiariter impoſitis Id. l. 4. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſec. 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>Leges non obligant,</hi> ſaith <hi>Suarez</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. <hi>The law doth not binde the Clergy by vertue of any Laick juriſdiction neither can Kings binde the Clergy by
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:112489:26"/>laying any ſpeciall Law upon them:</hi> and againe,<note n="d" place="margin">Peſona Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiastic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gaaudent immanit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e privi egio fort n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſolum in Criminibus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiasticis ſed civilibus. Id. ea. <hi>15. Sect. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall perſons are priviledged in Court, not onely in caſe of eccleſiasticall but of civill crimes.</hi> An immunity which a corrupt Clergy would be glad of.</p>
            <p>And therefore though there can <hi>be no reaſon</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived why a <hi>Prince</hi> profeſſing the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> ſhould decline to <hi>Popery:</hi> Yet you ſee there is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why a <hi>proud Prelacy</hi> and a <hi>corrupt Clergie</hi> ſhould <hi>under-hand</hi> indeavour to bring it in: and you ſee the <hi>method and wayes whereby</hi> they may compaſſe their deſignes and neither <hi>Prince nor people know nor ſee.</hi> Theſe were their <hi>pract ſes for many</hi> late yeares you all know, let any <hi>ingenous ſpirit judge of their intentions.</hi> I have onely let you ſee from whoſe <hi>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> they have drawne <hi>their ſhaftes;</hi> judge by that of the <hi>marke whereat they aymed.</hi> You have ſeene whoſe <hi>heifer</hi> it is they <hi>plowed with;</hi> judge by that of the <hi>ſeed they would have ſowne.</hi> If they never knew that <hi>a Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite</hi> had delivered theſe Rules for the <hi>altering of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in a Chriſtian ſtate,</hi> they were very unhappie in complying ſo exactly with them when they did not <hi>know them.</hi> And what can wee <hi>thinke</hi> but that they were <hi>acted</hi> by the ſame <hi>Genius or the ſame Angelus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formans,</hi> that the <hi>Ieſuite</hi> was, when he penned them. But if they did know (as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is moſt probable they did) that <hi>theſe</hi> were the <hi>rules,</hi> this the <hi>art</hi> delivered by a <hi>Ieſuite</hi> for the <hi>ſubverting the true reformed Religion,</hi> and the <hi>introduction of popery againe</hi> and yet did <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly</hi> and <hi>de induſtria</hi> conforme to them and made <hi>proofe of them,</hi> what can wee thinke was their intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but to alter our Religion. <hi>They had ſaid they ſhall not know nor ſee, till we are in the midſt of them and cauſe that worke to ceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:112489:27"/>
            <p>But <hi>bleſſed bee the Lord who hath not given us up as a prey unto their teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſſed bee the Lord,</hi> that by the hand of this <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> hath fruſtrated that <hi>plot. (We all hope) for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Information of ſome preſent practiſes of the adverſaries.</note>But did I ſay <hi>for ever?</hi> May we hope it? What? are <hi>our adverſaries</hi> all deſtroyed? or have they left of <hi>plotting?</hi> Neither; And yet I hope we may ſay, <hi>for ever. This great plot of altering Religion,</hi> prevented <hi>for ever.</hi> As for our <hi>adverſaries</hi> verily, if ever the did <hi>ſtraine</hi> their <hi>Witts</hi> to exceed themſelves in <hi>plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> miſchiefe, it hath been ſince this <hi>Parliament.</hi> Such a <hi>ſuccenturiation</hi> there hath beene of <hi>plotts</hi> that wee may ſay of them as ſhe <hi>of Gad. A Troope com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth.</hi> Many of them indeed have proved <hi>abortive, miſcarried</hi> before they came to a <hi>growth</hi> capable of <hi>full diſcovery</hi> and ſo are more <hi>eaſily denied</hi> then <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi> Beſides ſome <hi>ridiculous</hi> things have beene ſent forth into the <hi>publicke</hi> of purpoſe to <hi>outface</hi> the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>ſully</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of our <hi>deliverances</hi> from many and <hi>reall dangers,</hi> which poſſibly may be the reaſon why ſome men are ſo <hi>incredulous,</hi> they can ſee no <hi>adverſaries,</hi> they <hi>apprehend no dangers,</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> needs no <hi>guard;</hi> there is no <hi>neceſsity</hi> of ſettling the <hi>MILITIA</hi> of the Kingdome. If there bee any ſuch here and you bee men of reaſon hearken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>little.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Doe you not thinke, there are as many <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> in <hi>England now,</hi> as there were at the <hi>time of the powder Treaſon?</hi> I know not how there ſhould bee <hi>fewer</hi> but more; unleſſe the <hi>preaching</hi> of <hi>popiſh do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:112489:27"/>complying</hi> with <hi>popiſh ceremonies, ſetting</hi> up publike <hi>Maſſes, tolerating a convent of Friers, relax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the <hi>Lawes</hi> againſt <hi>popiſh Prieſts,</hi> bee a meanes to <hi>convert</hi> papiſts, there cannot be fewer then was at the time of the <hi>powder</hi> treaſon.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider whether the <hi>papiſts</hi> have any better <hi>doctrines, d ſpoſitions, principles now</hi> then they <hi>had then. Their faith was then faction; their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Rebellion,</hi> in the judgement of the <hi>State</hi> who ſpake as they found. <hi>Have</hi> they ſince <hi>changed</hi> their <hi>faith, altered</hi> their <hi>Religion,</hi> that our <hi>State</hi> ſhould alter their <hi>judgement</hi> of them? Doe they not yet <hi>hold</hi> it, as lawfull, as <hi>meritorious</hi> to <hi>promove</hi> the <hi>Catholicke cauſe Vi vel fraude,</hi> by violence or <hi>treaſon,</hi> now as they did then? Have they retracted that <hi>doctine</hi> of theirs.<note n="a" place="margin">Reges et princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes non Romano-Catholici poſſunt de jure occidi etiam à privatâ perſona &amp; illud factum est gener<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, cum virtute conjunctum &amp; heroicum. Compa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m cum maximis &amp; ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a Laude dignis factis eſſe, Sanctiſſimum, humaniſſimum, digniſſimum, la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>datiſsimum, commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <p>Es qui in vitam talium Regum es principium conjuram, eſſe animoſos machinato res forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinem Eorum eſſe pluſquam humanam, ſupplicia eorum non niſi vera martyria appellanda qui fint aliquand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> praemium accepturi in vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>â aeternâ: Francis: de Veron. Conſtant. in Apol: <hi>Part. 1. Cap. 7.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>That Kings &amp; Princes which are not Roman Catholicks</hi> may be lawfully <hi>killed</hi> by any private perſon, And that the <hi>killing</hi> of <hi>them</hi> is a <hi>generous, vertuous, heroick exploit? To bee compared with the greatest and moſt praiſe worthy actions? A most holy, worthy, commendable, praiſe-full work? Thoſe that conſpire against the life of ſuch Kings and Princes are magnanimous perſons.</hi> Their <hi>courage is more than humane, heroick, divine.</hi> Their <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments are true martyrdome, they ſhall receave reward in the kingdom of Heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:112489:28"/>
            <p>Have they yet revoked that <hi>aſſertion?</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Neceſſarium quocunque caſu Religionem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmari etiam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orte Regum. <hi>Id. pat. 2 c 12 &amp;. 15.</hi>
               </note> It is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in any caſe that Religion be maintained even with the death of Kings. Or that of the <hi>Ieſuite</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Non paſſe ab a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri ullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s meritorium opus quam ſi Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem interfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eret Anton. <hi>Arnold. in Ora: contra Ieſutias.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radius</hi> to <hi>Barerius.</hi> That <hi>there could not be a more merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious work, then for him to kill the King.</hi> Do they not to <hi>this day</hi> honour <hi>Garnet</hi> that <hi>Arch powder Traitour</hi> as a <hi>Saint?</hi> have not their<note n="a" place="margin">Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nel: a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid. in Apocal: <hi>cap. 7. ver. 3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Late Writers crowned</hi> him with <hi>freſh Encomiasticks?</hi> And hath not our <hi>State</hi> reaſon to have a <hi>watchfull</hi> and <hi>prudent jealouſie</hi> over men <hi>informed</hi> with ſuch deſperate <hi>principles</hi> and thus <hi>incouraged</hi> to all <hi>bloudy deſignes?</hi> ſpecially ſuch of them as are <hi>Ieſuites</hi> and <hi>Seminaries</hi> of whom we may truely ſay as <hi>Amilcar</hi> did of his ſonnes, Hee bred them,<note n="b" place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
               <hi>Tanquam leoninos catulos in pernitiem Romani imperij;</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Se quam primu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſſet hoſtem fore populo Rom capi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>talem Liv: li. <hi>21 c. 1.</hi> Appian: de bellis Hiſp:</note> 
               <hi>as Lions Whelpes for the deſtruction of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire.</hi> So doe they breed their <hi>Novices,</hi> As <hi>Lions whelpes</hi> for the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Church and Kingdome.</hi> And as <hi>Hannibal</hi> when hee was but nine yeares <hi>old,</hi> ſwore upon the <hi>Altar</hi> of their Gods that as <hi>ſoone as hee was able hee would bee a deadly enemy to the people of Rome:</hi> So do they <hi>in effect ſweare as much againſt us.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Ad defendendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; retinendum papatum Rom: contra omnem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adjutor ero: Haereticos, Schismaticos &amp; qui alicut ex Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis noſtris ſucceſſoribus p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aedictis Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es fuerint perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quar &amp; impugna <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Szeged: ſpeculum Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficum.</note> 
               <hi>I will helpe to defend and maintaine the Roman papacy againſt every man: Heretickes and Schiſmaticks, And all ſuch as ſhall rebell againſt our Lord</hi> the Pope <hi>and all his ſucceſſors, I will perſecute and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</hi> The <hi>whole fry</hi> of them are <hi>Conjurati hoſtes Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae &amp; Reipublica</hi> They declared themſelves ſo in their <hi>powder treaſon:</hi> and <hi>as long as they retaine their old Religion,</hi> they cannot but <hi>retaine their old diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, there being <hi>papiſts</hi> among us now as <hi>there was at</hi> the time of the powder <hi>Treaſon.</hi> They
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:112489:28"/>being <hi>infected</hi> with as <hi>bloudy doctrines,</hi> and <hi>principles, now</hi> as then.</p>
            <p>Conſider <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Whether they may not <hi>pretend</hi> to themſelves as <hi>juſt cauſes</hi> to <hi>put them</hi> upon all blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and <hi>deſperate deſignes now,</hi> as <hi>then they</hi> did. Were they <hi>croſſed</hi> in their <hi>expectations</hi> of a <hi>tolleration</hi> of their <hi>Religion</hi> then? Their expectations were raiſed <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er now.</hi> They hoped for a <hi>revolting to their Religion,</hi> and are croſſed in that. Did they <hi>feare</hi> the <hi>State</hi> would make ſome further <hi>proviſion</hi> for the <hi>ſuppreſsing of popery then?</hi> And did they <hi>not feare</hi> the <hi>State</hi> would make ſome farther <hi>proviſion</hi> for the utter <hi>extirpation of it</hi> now? Were they ſo <hi>inraged then?</hi> Surely they are <hi>madde</hi> and <hi>deſperate</hi> now. Were their <hi>thoughts</hi> ſo <hi>full</hi> of <hi>bloud then? Sure</hi> they are <hi>full of hell now.</hi> And of a truth, if there had not beene <hi>one plot nor one treaſon diſcovered</hi> all this <hi>Parliament time:</hi> yet good reaſon why the Parliament ſhould <hi>upon theſe conſiderations</hi> arm the Kingdom for its <hi>defence.</hi> (And the <hi>whole Nation</hi> is bound to them for their care here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) to prevent our adverſaries, leaſt they <hi>ſhould ſay. Wee will come upon them and they ſhall neither know nor ſee till wee are in the midſt of them, and ſlay them and cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what need theſe <hi>Ambages?</hi> when the <hi>bloudy monſters</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſpeake out and tell all the world, the <hi>warre they have kindled, is againſt the puritan Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> So that <hi>ex profeſse</hi> there hath been <hi>treaſon</hi> againſt this <hi>Parliament,</hi> and our <hi>adverſaries have ſaid</hi> (varying the words of the Text a little,) <hi>Wee will come upon them,</hi> though <hi>they know and ſee it, and ſlay them, and cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, ô that <hi>Ireland</hi> had beene guilty alone!
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112489:29"/>That <hi>England, England</hi> had not beene conſcious of ſuch <hi>treacherous practiſes.</hi> But it is to too apparent now. That even in <hi>England,</hi> in the <hi>midst of us,</hi> in our <hi>hoſomes</hi> have beene the moſt <hi>dangerous,</hi> and <hi>deſperate practiſes</hi> againſt our <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> that ever yet were knowne. Let me not ſeeme to <hi>detract</hi> from the <hi>glory</hi> of that <hi>great deliverance,</hi> if I ſay, they doe <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed</hi> the <hi>powder Treaſon. Thoſe traitors</hi> layed their <hi>traines</hi> and <hi>fire workes</hi> in the <hi>bowels</hi> of the <hi>earth: Theſe have layd theirs</hi> (which every true loyall heart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> leeds to think of) in the <hi>boſome</hi> of our <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne. They covered their treaſon</hi> with <hi>earth:</hi> Theſe with <hi>Heaven:</hi> with <hi>pretences</hi> of <hi>defending</hi> the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant profeſsion,</hi> the <hi>prerogative</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>liberties</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> whereby <hi>they have</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>captivated</hi> many of the <hi>injudicious mul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>de;</hi> but even the <hi>Throne</hi> it ſelfe.<note place="margin">Lamen. 4 20.</note> 
               <hi>The breath of our noſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord is taken in their pitts; Of whom we ſaid, under his ſhadow we ſhall live.</hi> Their <hi>pretences</hi> have ſo farre prevailed with our <hi>Soveraigne.</hi> That he <hi>confides</hi> more in a <hi>popiſh partie</hi> then in a <hi>protestant Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezekiel 19.4.</note> 
               <hi>This is a lamentation, and must be for a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi> They now <hi>pretend</hi> to be all for the King, <hi>the King;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 19.15.</note> as much as the <hi>Iewes for Caſar.</hi> Wee have <hi>no King but Caeſar: no King but Caeſar.</hi> As if <hi>Caeſar</hi> had had no <hi>ſuch loyall Subjects</hi> in the <hi>world</hi> as the <hi>Iewes</hi> were: but when they had <hi>ſerved themſelves</hi> of <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>abuſed</hi> his power to the <hi>murdering of Chriſt,</hi> they ſoone diſcovered themſelves: and <hi>Caeſar</hi> had no ſuch <hi>deſperate rebels,</hi> and <hi>implacable enemies</hi> upon earth <hi>as they were.</hi> So the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and their <hi>faction</hi> cry out, The <hi>prerogative,</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar:</hi> as if the <hi>King</hi> had no ſuch <hi>ſubjects</hi> and <hi>friends</hi> upon earth <hi>as they are.</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:112489:29"/>But <hi>marke my words.</hi> If <hi>ever</hi> they can <hi>ſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> of His Majeſtie: and by the <hi>abuſe of his power</hi> have <hi>their wills,</hi> to <hi>murder Christ</hi> in His <hi>members and root out the Goſpell</hi> and the <hi>profeſſors of it</hi> (which Lord in mercy preſerve His Majeſty from) but if they once obtaine but this. If they <hi>doe not prove the moſt</hi> deadly and deſperate <hi>enemies</hi> His Majeſtie <hi>ever had, let mee dye the</hi> death of a <hi>falſe Prophet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſearcher of hearts</hi> knowes <hi>(Oh that our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne knew as well)</hi> how the <hi>hearts</hi> of all <hi>His loyall Proteſtant ſubjects bleed</hi> within them for the <hi>ſoule</hi> of our Soveraigne. To ſee his <hi>confidence removed from</hi> his true <hi>Proteſtant ſubjects,</hi> whom hee can <hi>only confide</hi> in, and whom <hi>Catholicke Princes</hi> truſt <hi>rather</hi> then thoſe of their <hi>owne Religion.</hi> To ſee, I ſay, his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences withdrawne from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em, and <hi>leaning</hi> upon a company of <hi>popiſh, blou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>es, whom no <hi>prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant prince</hi> but <hi>himſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>urſt</hi> truſt. <hi>Lord give thy judgements to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Doth not His <hi>Majeſtie</hi> know that with <hi>the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> proteſtants</hi> are <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes:</hi> and with <hi>Hereticke</hi> KINGS and Princes they take a <hi>ſhort courſe,</hi> have a quicke way of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch? Doth not His Majeſtie know, or will <hi>none</hi> of his <hi>great Divines</hi> informe him, That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Doctors</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Reges &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipes poſſunt de jure etiam a pr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatâ perſond occidi: Francis. de Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron ubi ſupra:</note> hold it lawfull for any <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vate perſon to kill</hi> a <hi>Hereticke King?</hi> Yea and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>though he bee not ſentenced, excommunitated,</hi> or <hi>depoſed</hi> by the Pope, if his hereſie be <hi>notorious</hi> ſaith<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cajetan,</hi> 22 <hi>ae.</hi> q. 4.2.2.</note> 
               <hi>Cajetan?</hi> Or if he be<note n="d" place="margin">Andreas Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daemon. <hi>Apol. pro</hi> Garnetto. <hi>c. 10. p. 276.</hi> Et Mariana de Rege &amp; Regis inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one <hi>Lib. 1. c. 6.7, 8. pag. 58.60.63.67.</hi> Fas est ſubditis Reges &amp; Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes quibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> viri graves haereſeos Crime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> impegerint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uavis Ratione è medio tollere.</note> 
               <hi>publikely defamed for an Hereticke;</hi> or ſo repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by grave and <hi>judicious men?</hi> Nay, that it is <hi>not onely lawfull,</hi> but<note n="e" place="margin">Obligati ſunt ſubduia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes haereticos depell a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os &amp; hujuſmodi prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes ſuos non tantuns le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>time poſſunt detu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bare ſed etiam ad hoc praecepto Divino &amp; vincu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ctil ſimo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> extrem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enen u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Creſwell in</hi> Philopat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>2 Num. 160.162.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>neceſſary:</hi> not onely that they <hi>may doe it</hi> but they <hi>are bound to doe it.</hi> And that <hi>by the command of God</hi> upon <hi>perill of their ſoules.</hi> And
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:112489:30"/>this is <hi>not a</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Vniverſa Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logorum Schola tenet, &amp; est certum ac de fide Quem cunque Principem Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianum ſi a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ano Catholi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Religione <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e deſtex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> voh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e it ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e sia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e &amp; Digatate ex ipſa vi juris Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ai &amp; huma ni: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oc que &amp; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te Omnem ſenten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iam Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificis. Et ſuld tos quoſcunque Liberos eſſe aboumi Iuramenti obliga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tione quoad de Obed entia praeſti tiſſens poſſeque &amp; debere bujus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undi hominem tanquam Apoſta tam ex dominatis eijcere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e alios inficjan. Creſw. <hi>Num. 137</hi> Non eſt propria Ieſui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arum ſed Totius Eccleſia (&amp; quiden. ab aniqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is Temporibus) conſcaſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cepta noſtra Doctrina eſt. Eudaem. <hi>Apol.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>private opinion,</hi> but the <hi>opinion of all their Divines, ana of their whole Church,</hi> if we may believe themſelves. Nay it is <hi>not only lawfull</hi> and neceſſary: but if<note n="g" place="margin">Pendet Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ianum Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um a Pontifice in hoc ut poſſit non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>um conſulere aut conſentire ut Regnum Regem ſibi pernitie. ſum deponat ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> praeciper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ogere ut id facias. Suares: defens: fid: <hi>Lib. 6. cap 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ct. 17.</hi>
               </note> people ſhould be loth to offer <hi>violence</hi> to their PRINCE <hi>the Pope may command and compell them to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Papiſts ſhall as <hi>publikely</hi> and <hi>unanimouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſclaime this Doctrine,</hi> as they <hi>have proclaimed it,</hi> And the <hi>Parl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ament broach</hi> ſuch doct i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> drinke them in. Then let His <hi>Majestie</hi> flye from his Parliament and <hi>proteſtant ſubjects</hi> to <hi>ſecure</hi> his life and Crowne among the Papiſts. But in the meane time, O what a piece of <hi>Arch Treaſon</hi> was it! By ſowing <hi>contention</hi> betweene His <hi>Majeſtie</hi> and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to draw His <hi>Majeſty</hi> to betray Himſelfe into the hands of a <hi>generation,</hi> that in <hi>Conſcience think</hi> they may <hi>kill him</hi> when they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nay</hi> are <hi>taught.</hi> That in <hi>conſcience</hi> they <hi>are bound to kill him,</hi> if he <hi>pleaſe not them</hi> in <hi>Matters</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>may</hi> with <hi>a Nodd</hi> from <hi>Rome be commanded to</hi> kill him. Oh what an inextricable labyrinth, have theſe wretches brought our Prince into, by perſwading him, <hi>The intentions</hi> of his <hi>Parliament</hi> are againſt his <hi>Dignity</hi> and <hi>prerogative?</hi> The <hi>Lord rebuke them</hi> that ſo <hi>perſwade him: Yea the Lord rebuke thee Satan.</hi> But what <hi>better ſuggeſtions</hi> can breath from them that are <hi>Parl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ament adverſaries</hi> from <hi>generation</hi> to <hi>generation. This</hi> is it that hath moved his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> to caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the <hi>armes of Papiſts: Where</hi> he is <hi>as ſafe</hi> as a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:112489:30"/>
               <hi>lambe</hi> in the <hi>middeſt</hi> of <hi>wolves.</hi> Suppoſe that party (<hi>pretending his prerogative</hi> and thereby ſeducing a great part of the Kingdome to aſſiſt them.) Suppoſe they prevaile.</p>
            <p>What a condition is his Majeſty in? <hi>Either</hi> he is in danger of <hi>loſing his Religion,</hi> and being <hi>reconciled to Rome, Or</hi> if not, <hi>of loſing his life and forfeiting his Crown</hi> from <hi>himſelf</hi> and his <hi>posterity.</hi> Nay poſſibly he may <hi>lofe all, though</hi> he ſhould <hi>abandon Religion</hi> and <hi>be reconciled to Rome.</hi> For ſo <hi>Simanca</hi> determines.<note n="h" place="margin">Si Reges aut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Principes Chriſtian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti ſunt Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tici protinus ſubjecti &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalli ab eorum Dominio li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berantur, Nec jus hoc recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabunt quamvis. poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e à reconcilian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Eccleſiae &amp; propter haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin non ſolum Rex regno pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatur, ſed et<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iam ejus filii à regni ſucceſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne pelluntur. Simanca de Occult. tit. 42. ſee. 2</note> 
               <hi>If Kings or other Chriſtian Princes be turned Heretikes the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſubjects are preſently freed from their Dominion, neither ſhall they recover their right againe though they be afterwards reconciled to the Church. And as a King looſeth his kingdome by Hereſy ſo his children loſe their right of ſucceſsion.</hi> And to look no farther then <hi>Henry the fourth of France.</hi> Did his <hi>being reconciled to Rome, ſecure</hi> either <hi>his life</hi> or <hi>Crown? Lord give thy judgments to the King. Lord give thy judgments to the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I but no fear of this. <hi>The Papiſts have taken the oathes</hi> of <hi>ſupremacy</hi> and <hi>allegeance.</hi> And what are we the better? An <hi>oath</hi> upon the <hi>conſcience</hi> of a <hi>Papiſt</hi> is like a <hi>collar</hi> upon an <hi>Apesneck:</hi> that he <hi>will ſlip on for</hi> his <hi>Masters pleaſure,</hi> and <hi>ſlip</hi> off againe <hi>for his owne.</hi> Hear but how <hi>Paſcenius</hi> ſcoffes <hi>King Iames</hi> for the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention</hi> of that <hi>oath</hi> and you will ſee <hi>his ſonn hath</hi> little cauſe to truſt <hi>them</hi> for all their taking it.<note n="a" place="margin">Vide in tantâ aſtutiâ, quanta ſit ſimplicitas. Iuramentum tot circumſtantiis connexuiſſe exiſtimabat, ut ſalvâ conſcientiâ, nullâ ratione a quoquam diſſolui poſſit. Sed videre non potuit ſi Pontifex juramentum diſſolverit, omnesejus Nexus ſive de fidelitate Regi praeſtandâ ſive de diſpenſatione pariter non admittendâ pariter diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos fore. Imò ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d dicam admirabilius. Iuramentum ſi iniuſtum apertè declaretur Neminem obligat. Sed ipſo facto nullum eſt. Regis vero juramentum iniuſtum eſſe ab ipſo Eccleſiae Paſtore ſufficienjer declaratum eſt.</note> 
               <hi>He
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:112489:31"/>ſaith he,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide in tantâ aſtutia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quanta ſit ſimplicitas Iuramentum tot circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis connexuiſle exiſtimabat vt ſalvâ conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ nulla ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne à quo quam diſſoluipoſſet, ſed vidore non potuit ei Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ex luramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum diſſoluerit omnes eius Nexus ſive de fidelitate Regi praeſtanda ſive de diſpenſatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne pariter non admittenda pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riter diſſolutos fore &amp;c. Vides igitur jam in fumum abiiſſe illius obligationem, ut vinculum quod à Sapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus ferreum putabatur mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſit quam ſtramincum Paſcenius in Reſp. ad Epiſc. monit. Iacobi Regis. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.21.</note> 
               <hi>how ſimple they are, in all their craft: he thought he had compoſed an oath with ſo many particular cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, that it could not with a ſafe conſcience be diſpenſed with: but he could not ſee that if the Pope looſed the oath, all the knots of it whither concerning allca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to the King, or not ſuffering the oath to be diſpenſed with, they are all untied. Yea that which is more admirable. If the oath be publickly declared to be unjuſt, it bindes none,</hi> but <hi>ipſo facto is made void. Now the Pope hath ſufficiently declared this oath of the Kings to be unjuſt; ſo that the obligation of it vaniſhes into ſmoake and that bond, which thoſe wiſe men thought to be as ſtrong as braſſe is leſſe then a ſtraw.</hi> And now what Faith can his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty give to or what Confidence can his Majeſty have in the oath of theſe men?</p>
            <p>And yet as if it were not enough. To <hi>withdraw</hi> the <hi>heart</hi> of <hi>our Soveraign</hi> from confiding in <hi>his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> The <hi>venome</hi> of this <hi>treaſon reaches</hi> farther. And as <hi>Achitophel</hi> knowing that if <hi>Abſalon</hi> were recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to his <hi>Father</hi> againe, it would <hi>be his destruction,</hi> put <hi>Abſalon</hi> upon ſuch a <hi>buſineſſe</hi> as he knew was <hi>a ſcarec capable</hi> of <hi>reconciliation.</hi> So this <hi>curſed faction</hi> knowing that upon <hi>union</hi> between his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> followes their <hi>deſerved ruine:</hi> have <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled</hi> yea even <hi>compelled</hi> his <hi>Majestie</hi> to that, which <hi>(if any thing)</hi> might make the breach between his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> and his ſubjects incurable. Oh that <hi>vaſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion</hi> of <hi>Engliſh bloud</hi> which hath bin already not only in <hi>Ireland</hi> but in <hi>England!</hi> The <hi>ſunne</hi> hath <hi>not ſeen ſo many carkaſſes</hi> of <hi>Engliſh</hi> men lying upon their <hi>native ſoile</hi> in <hi>many hundred yeares.</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> ſee and <hi>avenge</hi> it upon <hi>them</hi> that are the <hi>originall cauſe</hi> of this bloud-ſheading. <hi>The violence that is done</hi> to <hi>me</hi> and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:112489:31"/>my <hi>fleſh</hi> be upon thee, ô <hi>Papacy,</hi> ſhall the <hi>Inhabitante</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſay. And my <hi>bloud</hi> upon thee, <hi>ô Prelacy,</hi> ſhall <hi>England</hi> ſay <hi>That That's</hi> the <hi>Helena</hi> for whoſe ſake all <hi>theſe warres are.</hi> For the <hi>defence</hi> of the <hi>Prelacy</hi> the <hi>Scotck</hi> warre was <hi>commenced</hi> (though P crogative and Monarchy was pretended) and for <hi>the ſame</hi> we may conceive the warre of <hi>England</hi> is purſued. We may ſay to that <hi>faction</hi> as <hi>Ioah</hi> did to <hi>David.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam</hi> 19.6.</note> 
               <hi>Thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeſt neither Prince nor ſervants for this day I perceave that if Abſalon had lived and all we had dyed, it had pleaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thee well.</hi> They <hi>regard</hi> neither <hi>Prince</hi> nor <hi>people</hi> for we may <hi>eaſily perceave;</hi> that if <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland imbrue</hi> themſelves in <hi>one anothers blouds; or England</hi> tear out its <hi>owne bowells,</hi> though <hi>all we dye ſo</hi> the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> ſurvive, they would be well pleaſen. <hi>Shall they eſcape by their iniquity? thou Lord in tey diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure ſhalt cast them down.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for our <hi>Soveraign.</hi> Thou <hi>ô God</hi> in whoſe <hi>hands</hi> the hearts of <hi>Kings</hi> are, <hi>free</hi> his <hi>heart</hi> from the <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells</hi> and ingagements of <hi>miſcheivous</hi> men and <hi>men of bloud. Give him a true underſtanding</hi> of <hi>and a due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence</hi> in the <hi>loyall affections</hi> of <hi>his Proteſtant ſubjects.</hi> Bring <hi>him</hi> back among us <hi>rather</hi> in the <hi>prayers</hi> and <hi>tears</hi> then in the <hi>blouds</hi> of his <hi>people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you <hi>my brethren</hi> ſo many as have any <hi>ſparke of loyalty</hi> in your breaſtes and I hope you are all full of it, deſire and ſeeke the ſame thing, yee of this <hi>City:</hi> Yee of the <hi>honorable Nation</hi> of the <hi>Scots</hi> be not yee the <hi>last to bring the King back to his houſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>Yee are his brethren, yee are his bone, and his fleſh, why ſhould yee be the laſt in bringing the King back to his houſe againe? even</hi> to <hi>his houſe</hi> of <hi>Parliament?</hi> Aſſuredly if his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties life were bound up in one haire of his head,</hi> as
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:112489:32"/>
               <hi>Niſus was,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cui ſple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> didus Oſtro, Inter ho noratos medio de vertice ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos crinis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haerebat magni fiducia Regni. <hi>Ovid. Metam.</hi> Application the third by way of Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation firſt to the Parliament</note> he might be <hi>more ſecure</hi> there then he can be among <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Cavaliers</hi> if <hi>every haire</hi> of his <hi>head were a life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come to a few words of Exhortation. Firſt <hi>To you the Members of the honorable Houſe of Parliament.</hi> Secondly, To you <hi>the reſt of my brethren.</hi> Firſt for you <hi>honourable</hi> and <hi>beloved.</hi> This <hi>text,</hi> this <hi>truth</hi> tells you <hi>what you muſt look to meet with. God</hi> hath <hi>opened</hi> to you a great <hi>doore</hi> of <hi>opportunity</hi> for the <hi>promoving</hi> of his <hi>Churches</hi> good but <hi>their are many adverſaries. God</hi> hath <hi>called you</hi> together to a great <hi>work:</hi> but you <hi>muſt look our adverſaries will do their utmoſt either</hi> by <hi>craft or cruelty to cauſe the work to ceaſe.</hi> That which <hi>our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> ſpake to his <hi>Diſciples</hi> to confirme their <hi>hearts</hi> againſt <hi>the perſecutions of their adverſaries.</hi> The <hi>ſame ſay I to you</hi> to <hi>ſteel your hearts againſt the oppoſitions of your adverſaries.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.</note> So <hi>ſaith our Saviour perſecuted they the Prophets that were before you.</hi> The ſame ſay I to you. So <hi>maligned they</hi> the <hi>Parliaments</hi> that <hi>were before you.</hi> So <hi>ſlandered they the Parliaments that were before you.</hi> So <hi>plotted they againſt the Parliaments that were before you.</hi> So <hi>ſaid they of them. We will come upon them and they ſhall neither know nor ſee till we are in the middeſt of them, and ſlay them and cauſe the work to ceaſe.</hi> Therefore <hi>be you in nothing terrified of your adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Durate &amp; voſmetrebus ſervate ſecundis.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Bear</hi> up againſt <hi>their oppoſitions. After ages</hi> ſhall keep <hi>thankeſgiving dayes</hi> for <hi>your deliverance,</hi> as you now do <hi>for the deliverance of your forefathers.</hi> You have the <hi>rememberance</hi> of that great <hi>deliverance</hi> as an
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:112489:32"/>
               <hi>incouragement</hi> to your hearts <hi>this day.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Druſ. Apopht<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Qui cuſtodivit Patres, custodiet etiam filios.</hi> Deliverances <hi>paſt</hi> are the <hi>pledges</hi> of <hi>future deliverances.</hi> And this advantage you have above your forefathers. <hi>That</hi> whereas <hi>they</hi> neither <hi>knew</hi> their danger nor ſought <hi>deli verance,</hi> yet were they <hi>delivered. You ſee</hi> your danger, <hi>flee</hi> to <hi>God</hi> by <hi>prayers, tears, faſtings</hi> for <hi>deliverance:</hi> You have the <hi>pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs,</hi> and <hi>tears</hi> of all the <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> poaſting <hi>inceſſantly</hi> to <hi>Heaven</hi> upon <hi>the ſame Embaſſage</hi> and can <hi>you</hi> faile of <hi>deliverance? Remember</hi> againe the goodneſſe and greatneſſe of your <hi>cauſe,</hi> and what <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid to <hi>Melancthon.</hi> When upon that <hi>oppoſition,</hi> which the <hi>German reformation</hi> mett with all, he was much <hi>troubled a</hi> and <hi>diſquieted</hi> in his ſpirit,<note place="margin">Cum effet Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo admodum anxio non tam ſui quam ipſius exitus &amp; poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis causâ: Lutherus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et, vt quia non hominum ſed omnipotentis Dei ſit hoc ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotium omni depoſirâ ſollicitudine totam molem in illum reii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat. Cur, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, te Cruci as? ſi Filium ſuum Deus pro nobis impendit, quid trepidamus? quid metuimus? quid an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimur &amp; triſtamur? an Satanas eſt illo potentior? Cur mundum â Chirſto debellatum reformidamus? Si malam cauſam defendimus: cur non mutamus propoſitum, ſi-piam atque jaſtam cur Dei promiſſis non confidimus? praeter vitam certè nihil nobis Sata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas etipere poteſt; at vivit tamen &amp; in ſempiternum regnat Chriſtus ſub cujus tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elâ veritas eſt. Peccatores quidem ſumus non uno modo ſed tamen Chriſtus idcircò non eſt mend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x cujus cauſam agimus. Fremant Reges atque populi quantum volent', qui caelos inhabitat, deridebit cos. Cauſam hanc Deus abſque concilio noſtro gubernavit ad hoc uſque tempus &amp; protexit, is quoque ad optatum ſinem tandem perducet. Sleid com. l. 7.</note> 
               <hi>not</hi> for his own <hi>ſake</hi> out for the <hi>works ſake</hi> and the <hi>iſſue</hi> of it, and <hi>poſterityes</hi> ſake, <hi>Luther</hi> gives him councell. <hi>That ſeeing the buſineſſe was not mans but Almighty Gods. Laying aſide all care he would caſt the whole weight of it upon him. Why</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>do you vex your ſelf? If God have beſtowed his Sonne upon us, why are we afraid? what tremble we at? why are we diſtracted ſadded? Is Satan stronger then he? Why feare we the world which Chriſt hath conquered? If we defend an evill cauſe, why do we not change our purpoſe? If the cauſe be holy and juſt, why do we not trust Gods promiſes?</hi> Certainly <hi>there is nothing beſide our lives that Sathan can ſnatch from us:</hi> and <hi>though we dye, Chriſt lives and reignes for ever, under
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:112489:33"/>whoſe tuition the truth is.</hi> We are indeed <hi>ſinners more wayes th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n one, but our ſinnes ſhall never make Chriſt (whoſe cauſe we are ingaged in) a lier.</hi> Let the Kings of <hi>the earth and the people</hi> rage <hi>as much as they will: he that ſits in heaven ſhall laugh them to ſcorn.</hi> God <hi>hath hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ruled and defended this cauſe without our councells he alſowill bring it to the deſired end.</hi> May not <hi>all this</hi> be applied unto you? but <hi>ſpecially</hi> this <hi>laſt clauſe?</hi> God <hi>without your councells, above your councells</hi> by <hi>naked</hi> and <hi>immediate providences</hi> hath <hi>carried</hi> on <hi>his work</hi> in <hi>your hands</hi> hitherto: and <hi>he will give it the deſired, prayed for iſſue: you may be confident of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Only:</hi> as your <hi>cauſe</hi> is <hi>good,</hi> ſo <hi>ſee</hi> that <hi>your wayes</hi> be <hi>good.</hi> Remembring what the <hi>holy ghoſt</hi> ſaith; <hi>Proverb.</hi> 16.7. <hi>When a mans wayes pleaſe God he maketh his very enemies to be at peace with him. Let</hi> your <hi>perſonall</hi> wayes. Your <hi>publick wayes. What</hi> you <hi>act</hi> as <hi>men. What</hi> you <hi>act</hi> as <hi>Parliament men, pleaſe God:</hi> and <hi>reape</hi> the <hi>fruit</hi> of it in <hi>peace</hi> with or <hi>triumph</hi> over <hi>all your enemies.</hi> For <hi>your perſonall wayes,</hi> your <hi>converſations</hi> as <hi>men.</hi> Oh, me thinkes, if <hi>any</hi> of <hi>you</hi> when you came to this <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly</hi> were of <hi>vaine converſations</hi> (as other men are.) Yet ſo <hi>many prayers, ſo many ſermons, ſo many Faſt-dayes, ſo many dangers, ſo many deliverances, ſuch va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety</hi> of <hi>admirable, aſtoniſhing providences,</hi> as you have known: ſhould have prevailed with your hearts <hi>to abandon all,</hi> and become <hi>eminently gracious, exact</hi> in all your <hi>wayes.</hi> But if <hi>not.</hi> If there be yet <hi>any ſinne</hi> found upon <hi>any of you.</hi> If any <hi>of you be conſcious</hi> that <hi>any</hi> of <hi>his wayes:</hi> though <hi>never ſo ſecret,</hi> be <hi>diſpleaſing</hi> unto <hi>God:</hi> Let me in the <hi>feare of God</hi> and in <hi>the bowells</hi> of <hi>our Lord Ieſus</hi> beſeech you. As you <hi>deſire ſucceſſe</hi> either to <hi>your councells,</hi> or <hi>armes.</hi> As you <hi>tender</hi> the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:112489:33"/>good of <hi>your native country</hi> (which I know is <hi>deare</hi> unto <hi>you,</hi> why elſe ſhould you <hi>put your lives</hi> in <hi>your hands</hi> to do it ſervice?) Oh <hi>breake off your ſinnes by repentance:</hi> why ſhould <hi>men</hi> of <hi>brave</hi> and <hi>honourable ſpirits, ſtaine</hi> and <hi>diminiſh</hi> their <hi>glory</hi> by <hi>any one ſinne?</hi> That as it was ſaid of <hi>Naaman</hi> he was <hi>a mighty man of vaiour: but a leper.</hi> So of any of you. He is <hi>a prudent man, abrave ſpeaker,</hi> but — <hi>a profound statiſt: a worthy patriott</hi> but — Oh let there be no <hi>But,</hi> For Gods ſake, be you all as the <hi>Sunne,</hi> without <hi>one ſpott.</hi> Why ſhould a man <hi>denude</hi> himſelf of the <hi>protection</hi> of the <hi>Almighty</hi> for <hi>one</hi> ſinn? It was ſaid of <hi>Achilles</hi> that he was. <hi>Styge armatus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fulgent. Myth.</note> But <hi>he</hi> that <hi>repents</hi> of his ſinns that <hi>believes</hi> in <hi>Chriſt</hi> whoſe <hi>wayes pleaſe God is Caelo, Chriſto, Deo, armatus:</hi> armed with <hi>heaven,</hi> with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with <hi>God.</hi> Would <hi>any at ſuch a time as this, in ſuch a ſervice as yours be without this</hi> armour? <hi>Oh let your wayes pleaſe God,</hi> and you ſhall not neede feare <hi>your adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as your <hi>perſonall wayes:</hi> So your <hi>publick wayes.</hi> The <hi>things</hi> that you <hi>tranſact as publick perſons:</hi> let them be <hi>exact. Walke</hi> and <hi>work</hi> by <hi>rule. Appelles</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked why he uſed ſuch exact care in limning pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures made this anſwer: <hi>Pingo aeternitati:</hi> I limne for eternity. The <hi>things</hi> that you have now <hi>to do,</hi> are <hi>not only for the preſent but future ages.</hi> Your <hi>actions</hi> will <hi>live</hi> in the <hi>memory of men,</hi> as <hi>long as men ſhall live upon earth.</hi> You work for <hi>eternity:</hi> Therefore be <hi>exact:</hi> work by <hi>rule,</hi> by <hi>line</hi> and <hi>plummet.</hi> Let all <hi>your aimes</hi> be <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>good.</hi> Fix your eye upon <hi>Gods glory.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Druſ. Apopth.</note> 
               <hi>Quicquid agas, propter Deum agas.</hi> Let that be your <hi>motto</hi> which was his. <hi>Propter te Domine: propter te.</hi> Aime <hi>at God in all. And walke with God in all.</hi> See <hi>the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:112489:34"/>pillar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> fire go ng before you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>orant, That your <hi>taking up of armes</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpute.</hi> Now no time for that. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay. <hi>It is no more</hi> then other of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of Chriſt</hi> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>driven to</hi> before, you, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>French,</hi> the <hi>high</hi> and <hi>low Dutch Churches.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Germany</hi> when the <hi>Proteſtant Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> were tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g about a <hi>defenſive league</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">In con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aiue adhibin fuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> non lure n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul imo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: Lu h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtratu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ reuſten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um &amp; ext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bat e us h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d reliber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus (um u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liber tione pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uris doce r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt Legibus eſſe perm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſum reſiſtere non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunquam, &amp; nune in eum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum de quo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eges me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tionem f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rem eſſe deductam: Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti erus iogen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> profice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hoc neſciviſſ. Et qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a Leges Politicas Eva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliam a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m. pugnet ant ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oleat: deinoe quoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m cubio &amp; f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmidoloſo multa poſſunt accidere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ta ut non modo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us ipſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae vis ae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eceſſitas arma nobis porrigat defenſionis cuisa faedus poſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niri dicit. ſive Caeſar ipſe ſive quis alius fortè bellum eius Nomine faciat. Sle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> not only <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers</hi> but <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vines</hi> were called to give their <hi>councell</hi> in the thing. <hi>Luther</hi> who had <hi>always</hi> taught, <hi>That the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ought not to be reſiſted,</hi> and in the times of the <hi>Anabaptiſticall tumults,</hi> had written <hi>a book to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</hi> Being <hi>one in the Conſultation,</hi> and hearing the <hi>lawyers</hi> declare. <hi>That it was permitted by the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mextall Lawes; ſometimes to reſiſt: and that now matters were brought to that very ſtate of which the Lawes made mention. Luther</hi> did ingenuouſly <hi>profeſſe</hi> that <hi>he knew not ſo much before.</hi> And <hi>becauſe the Goſpell doth not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugn nor aboliſh nationall Lawes.</hi> And <hi>becauſe in ſuch a time as that was, uncertain, and full of feare, many things might fall out</hi> ſo as <hi>not only Lawe</hi> but <hi>conſcience and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity might put armes into their hands:</hi> Therefore he did conclude. <hi>They might lawfully enter into a league of defence whether</hi> Caelat <hi>himſelf, or</hi> any other <hi>in his name ſhould make warr upon them.</hi> And preſently <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed a book:</hi> therein <hi>admoniſhing all men that they ſhould not yeild obedience</hi> to <hi>the Magiſtrats</hi> command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them unto that warr againſt the league.</p>
            <p>I know many in the Land charge <hi>the preachers of the Kingdome,</hi> and thoſe that have <hi>petitioned you ſo</hi> often for <hi>reformation</hi> in <hi>doctrine, worſhip</hi> and <hi>diſcipline</hi> as the <hi>kindlers</hi> and <hi>formenters</hi> of this <hi>unnaturall warre.</hi> But <hi>O Lord if we have done this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if there be ſuch iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:112489:34"/>in our hands, then let the enemy perſecute our ſoule and take i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>let them tread down our life upon the earth, and lay our honour in the duſt. We have not deſired this wofull d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y O Lord thou knoweſt it, our deſire</hi> was to have obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the <hi>eſtabliſhment of religion in purity</hi> &amp; <hi>peace w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blond, ô Lord thou knowest it. Quod ſi non aliter.</hi>—</p>
            <p>But if the <hi>ſinnes</hi> of <hi>England</hi> bee ſuch, and the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements of our adverſaries to their ſuperſtitious wayes</hi> be ſuch. That there <hi>is no other way</hi> to have <hi>popery</hi> caſt out, the <hi>Church reformed</hi> the <hi>Goſpell aſſured</hi> to <hi>us</hi> and our <hi>poſterity</hi> then this. <hi>Hac mercede placent. The will of the Lord be done.</hi> Goe you on undauntedly in that bleſſed <hi>worke</hi> of reformation. Thinke you heare <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeaking to you as <hi>Caeſar</hi> did to his <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie-man</hi> in a ſtorme. <hi>Perge contra Tempeſtatem forti Animo Caeſarem fers &amp; fortunam Caeſaris.</hi> Beare up cou agiouſly againſt the ſtorme you carry <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Caeſars</hi> fortune. Thinke you heare <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſo ſaying unto you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pergite contra Tempeſtatem forti Animo Chriſtum fertis &amp; fortunam, Eccleſiam, gloriam Chriſti. Beare up</hi> couragiouſly againſt the <hi>ſtorme;</hi> you carry <hi>Chriſt</hi> with you, and the <hi>Church</hi> the <hi>fortune,</hi> the <hi>glory of Chriſt.</hi> If the <hi>Tempeſts</hi> and <hi>flouds</hi> of the ungodly riſe againſt you, remember you have not only the <hi>ſighes</hi> and <hi>teares</hi> of <hi>Gods people</hi> for you, but Chriſt <hi>imbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with you,</hi> who is able to rebuke the <hi>ſtormes</hi> and <hi>command a calme.</hi> You are a <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>prayers</hi> and <hi>teares,</hi> if ever any: and as <hi>Amb.</hi> ſaid to <hi>Auſtins</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Non poteſt perire tantarum lachrimarum filius.</hi> A Child of ſo <hi>many prayers and teares cannot miſcarry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet as you are to be <hi>couragious,</hi> ſo to be <hi>caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</hi> As to bee <hi>confident,</hi> ſo <hi>vigilant:</hi> To have a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:112489:35"/>
               <hi>watchfull eye over,</hi> and a <hi>prudent care</hi> to ſuppreſſe <hi>your adverſaries.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Herodot: in Terpſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. <hi>c. 1 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Darius</hi> the <hi>Perſian</hi> being inraged againſt the <hi>Athenians</hi> by a <hi>treachery</hi> of theirs, layed this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction upon one of his ſervants, <hi>that alwayes</hi> as hee ſate at meate he ſhould thrice cry, <hi>Here memento A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenienſium.</hi> You need no ſuch Monitor. <hi>This fifth of November,</hi> in its yearely revolution cries loud in your yeares. <hi>Domini memento te papiſtarum.</hi> Not ſo much to <hi>inrage you againſt their perſons,</hi> as againſt <hi>their Religion.</hi> Not to ſay as he did there. <hi>ô Iupiter,</hi> &amp;c <hi>Lord grant that I may be revenged upon the Athenians.</hi> Not to ſtudy revenge upon the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ſo much as upon <hi>popery,</hi> not to ſuppreſſe the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ſo much as to <hi>ſuppreſſe popery,</hi> if the one could be done without the other. What need there is of this, let a <hi>Divine that had ſearched</hi> into the bowels of <hi>popery</hi> tell you.<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Iohn white <hi>in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at</hi> Pau's <hi>Croſſe.</hi> Dicretum fuit in Conciltis Toleta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ut quiſquis ſuccedentium Temporum Regni ſortiretur apicem, non ante conſcenderet Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am ſedem qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inter Caetera Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramento pollice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur Nullum fe non Catholicum permiſſurum in ſuo Regno degere, ſed armis haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticos perſequere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Ribadeneira <hi>l. 1.</hi> de Principe chriſtiano: <hi>c. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtry</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>can neither ſtand with peace, nor piety. The State therefore that would have theſe things, hath juſt cauſe to ſuppreſſe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what courſe is to be taken for the ſuppreſſing of it? <hi>Shall wee take that courſe for the ſuppreſsing of popery</hi> which ſome of theirs <hi>preſcribe</hi> for the <hi>ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the truth. Decretum fuit in conſiliis Toletanis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>They made decrees in ſome of their counſels. That every King before he bee inſtalled ſhould, ſweare among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> things. <hi>That hee would permit no man to live in his Kingdom, that is not a Roman Catholick, but will pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue all Hereticks with the ſword.</hi> I know it is <hi>diſputed</hi> among <hi>Divines.</hi> Whether it be <hi>lawfull</hi> to uſe <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſory meanes</hi> in matters of <hi>Religion.</hi> And no leſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <hi>Politicians</hi> whither it would bee <hi>ſucceſſefull.</hi> I ſhall neither take <hi>upon mee</hi> to <hi>determine thoſe diſputes.</hi> Nor <hi>direct the wiſdome of the great councell</hi> of the <hi>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:112489:35"/>in a courſe for ſuppreſſing <hi>popery.</hi> Only in briefe the meanes to be uſed to this end are, <hi>either ſacred,</hi> or <hi>civill:</hi> Acts of <hi>Religion,</hi> or of <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For religious <hi>meanes,</hi> I conceive that as the re-eſtabliſhment of Popery in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes was an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>State</hi> and of the whole Kingdome aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in <hi>Parliament:</hi> ſo if the <hi>State,</hi> the Parliament now <hi>aſſembled</hi> would pleaſe to indict ſome <hi>Day</hi> or <hi>dayes</hi> of <hi>ſolemne, Nationall, profeſſed humiliation,</hi> for that ſinne of the <hi>Nation,</hi> (which as farre as I could ever learne, was never yet done) it might bee a happie meanes to <hi>expiate</hi> that <hi>ſinne,</hi> and to <hi>purge</hi> the <hi>Land</hi> from that bloud of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> which it yet groanes under, and would bleſſedly prepare the <hi>heart</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> for a more thorow perfect <hi>Reformation.</hi> We obſerve it in particular <hi>perſons</hi> that if they ſlide out of <hi>profane</hi> and <hi>ſinfull wayes, into wayes</hi> of more <hi>retiredneſſe</hi> without any evidence of a <hi>ſincere</hi> and <hi>proportionable Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> That <hi>Reformation</hi> ſeldome proves <hi>laſting</hi> or <hi>ſaving.</hi> I know not why the <hi>ſame</hi> may not bee verified in <hi>Nationall Reformations.</hi> And among other things which poſſibly might bee cauſes why the <hi>wrath of the Lord was not removed</hi> from <hi>Hieruſalem, notwithſtanding</hi> Joſiah's <hi>ſo glorious Reformation,</hi> this may bee one becauſe the Land was never humbled for the <hi>Idolatries</hi> or <hi>Bloudſheds</hi> of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> but looked upon the <hi>reformation</hi> as ſufficient without <hi>humiliation</hi> which verily hath been <hi>Englands</hi> courſe to this day: we have <hi>bleſſed</hi> our ſelves in a <hi>kinde of Reformation:</hi> But never tooke to heart the <hi>Idolatrous</hi> and <hi>bloudy Lawes</hi> enacted by our <hi>forefathers</hi> to bee humbled for them.</p>
            <p>Next to this as a ſecond meanes for the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:112489:36"/>of Popery, I would ſubjoy ne the caſting out from among us of all appearances of Popery; every that lookes like <hi>Rome,</hi> every thing of which the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts may ſay, <hi>this you borrowed from us.</hi> True it is the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> by Gods expreſſe commandement, bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed of the <hi>Aegyptians, Iewels of ſilver, and Iewels of Gold,</hi> but when they <hi>imployed</hi> thoſe <hi>Egyptian Iewels</hi> to <hi>Egyptian</hi> worſhip, and <hi>turned</hi> their Egyptian <hi>gold</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Egyptian <hi>God,</hi> you know what followed. I condemne not every thing received from Rome as <hi>ſimply evill:</hi> But certainely <hi>as long</hi> as the Papiſts ſee any ſuch <hi>things</hi> among us in our <hi>publike worſhip.</hi> They will but <hi>ſcorne</hi> us, and our Religion as imperfect, and <hi>unable</hi> to furniſh us in the ſervice of our <hi>God</hi> without being beholding unto them.</p>
            <p>The third Meanes is; To ridd the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Ministers,</hi> that, <hi>what by their corrupt doctrine,</hi> what by <hi>their abominable lives,</hi> have exceedingly <hi>hardned</hi> the Papiſts againſt our Religion and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened them in their owne.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, By complying as neare as <hi>poſsible may</hi> be with other reformed <hi>Churches</hi> in all things. The <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution</hi> you have put on for uniting with the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> is one of the <hi>bleſsed'st things for</hi> the utter <hi>ſubverſion of</hi> popery that hath beene ſince the firſt <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, Plant a faithfull, painefull, powerfull, Miniſtery through the Kingdome. And give <hi>mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> and incouragement anſwerable. But <hi>O Lord,</hi> in ſuch a corrupt <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Clergie</hi> and Univerſities, where ſhall we finde <hi>faithfull men</hi> to plant the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with? <hi>The harvest is great the labourers few, O pray
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:112489:36"/>yee the Lord of the Vineyard to ſend forth labourers into his harveſt. To give the word, that great may be the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of them that preach it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for <hi>Civill</hi> meanes of rooting out Popery, I ſhall wholly leave them to the Councell of the State.</p>
            <p>Only one thing more let me adde, which I cannot without ſinne forbeare.</p>
            <p>If ever you would root <hi>popery</hi> out of <hi>Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd,</hi> with the <hi>uttermost</hi> of your <hi>vigour</hi> proſecute the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of <hi>Ireland.</hi> If Popery prevaile to the <hi>ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> of the true Religion there: Doe not <hi>thinke you can prevaile</hi> to <hi>ſuppreſſe popery here.</hi> I know your <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticke affaires</hi> are great, your occaſions of expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vaſt; yet I remember what the <hi>Historian</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Roman State.</hi> There was nothing did more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the greatneſſe of their ſpirits, then that at ſuch a time, as <hi>Hanniball</hi> was even <hi>Ad portus.</hi> Their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fure <hi>exhauſted</hi> by long <hi>Warres,</hi> Their <hi>Armies routed</hi> diverſe times, The <hi>State at the loweſt ebbe</hi> that ever it was in: Yet even then; when a mighty <hi>Warre lay upon their</hi> backes, They did <hi>not remit the care of any affaires, though never ſo remote from them.</hi> And no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing did more make <hi>Hannibal</hi> deſpaire of taking <hi>Rome;</hi> Then that he heard, <hi>ſupplies of Souldiers were ſent out of the Citie into</hi> Spaine, <hi>even then,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 22. c. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>when he with his whole army lay before their walles.</hi> I know not whither any <hi>thing would more pleaſe God</hi> or procure a <hi>bleſsing upon your affaires at home,</hi> I am ſure <hi>ſcarce any thing</hi> would m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>dant your adverſaries at home</hi> and <hi>abroad,</hi> then to ſee you at ſuch a time as this, ſending ſupplies into <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you my <hi>brethren</hi> the reſt of you that <hi>ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exhortati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:112489:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:112489:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:112489:38"/>
               <hi>the Lord</hi> this day. Withdraw not your <hi>aſsiſtance</hi> from the honourable Houſes of <hi>Parliament,</hi> in that or any other worke ſo juſt, Honourable and pious. You ſee they meete with oppoſition from their <hi>adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries:</hi> impoſſible it is, it ſhould be otherwiſe. Oh let them not <hi>meete with diſcouragment</hi> from their <hi>friends,</hi> from their <hi>brethren.</hi> No queſtion it was worſe to <hi>Nehemiah</hi> to heare <hi>Iudah</hi> ſay. <hi>The ſtrength of the bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rers of burdens is decaied and there is ſo much rubbiſh, wee cannot build the wall:</hi> Then it was to heare the adverſaries ſay. <hi>We will come upon them and they ſhall neither know nor ſee till we are in the midst of them and play them, and cauſe the worke to ceaſe.</hi> That which the <hi>adverſaries</hi> ſaid was no more then <hi>he looked for.</hi> But this of <hi>Iudah</hi> was unexpected. O let not <hi>London</hi> ſay, let not <hi>England</hi> ſay. The <hi>ſtrength of the bearers of burdens is decaied.</hi> The expences of the <hi>Iriſh warre</hi> and of the <hi>Engliſh affaires</hi> are ſuch a burden, <hi>wee can beare no longer, our ſtrength is decaied:</hi> wee <hi>cannot build the wall: the worke must ceaſe.</hi> I know your <hi>burdens</hi> this way <hi>have been great, and in this City farre greater</hi> then in other places of the Kingdom, and are like to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſtill. For though I hope it is not in the <hi>purpoſes of God</hi> to deſtroy <hi>England,</hi> nor to deſtroy <hi>London,</hi> yet I have thought ſometimes: <hi>The purpoſe and intent of God hath beene</hi> to <hi>humble,</hi> and <hi>attenuate London,</hi> and <hi>England.</hi> For <hi>Englands</hi> long <hi>continued peace,</hi> had <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly increaſed</hi> Englands <hi>wealth,</hi> and the <hi>abundant creaſed of</hi> Englands <hi>wealth</hi> had proportionably <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed</hi> Englands <hi>pride.</hi> The age <hi>before us</hi> knew not that <hi>exceſſe</hi> of bravery in <hi>clothes</hi> and utenſils that we were growne unto. And the <hi>generation growing</hi> up, was like to <hi>exceed us in both.</hi> God ſaw us labour
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:112489:38"/>ſo dangerouſly of a <hi>plethory</hi> as his wiſdome and <hi>love</hi> judged it <hi>needfull</hi> to <hi>abate and exhauſt our fulneſſe</hi> at leaſt ſo much as is ſuper fluous, and not <hi>matter of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence,</hi> but <hi>matter of pride</hi> unto us: which if we can <hi>willingly</hi> and chearefully <hi>reſigne up to the diſpoſall of God</hi> we may poſſibly thereby <hi>obtaine</hi> and ſecure our <hi>lives, Lawes, Religion,</hi> the things that are, or <hi>ſhould be deareſt to us.</hi> But if we hugge our <hi>wealth,</hi> when God would have us let it goe, Take heed we <hi>loſe</hi> not <hi>that,</hi> and all the reſt. Me thinkes I <hi>reade</hi> it in the <hi>foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteppes of God towards England. God</hi> hath ſaid. <hi>I will abate the wealth and pride of England.</hi> Me thinkes the <hi>ſucceſsion</hi> of theſe <hi>three warres</hi> within theſe <hi>few yeares</hi> (which comes not without the ſpeciall <hi>providence</hi> of that <hi>God who ruleth in the kingdomes of men</hi>) the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences of all which muſt lye upon <hi>England,</hi> ſpeaks it. <hi>That the purpoſe of God is to abate the pride and wealth of</hi> England. And me thinkes we ſhould ſay as <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiboſheth</hi> did, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.30. Yea let him <hi>take all for as much as my Lord the King is returned againe in peace to his owne houſe:</hi> might we but ſee our <hi>Soveraigne Lord the King</hi> brought in <hi>peace againe to his owne houſe,</hi> and to His Houſes of <hi>Parliament.</hi> Might we but <hi>ſee the King of Kings upon his holy hill of Zion. Chriſt in his beauty, on his Throne.</hi> The <hi>Church reformed, truth</hi> and <hi>peace eſtabliſhed: let him take all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I perſwade my ſelfe every <hi>honeſt heart</hi> that is <hi>loyall</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> to the <hi>publicke weale</hi> would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſpeake it and ſeale it, did not our <hi>adverſaries</hi> by their <hi>crafty inſinuations</hi> indeavour to divide as much <hi>between</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> and people as they have done <hi>betweene</hi> the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament.</hi> That would
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:112489:39"/>faine perſwade the <hi>people of this Nation,</hi> with the <hi>Ape</hi> in <hi>the emblem</hi> to cut in under the arme of the tree whereon <hi>they ſit and</hi> plunge themſelves into <hi>a gulph</hi> and <hi>ſea of miſery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this purpoſe as they <hi>have tolde his Majestie,</hi> ſo now they <hi>tell the people.</hi> That the <hi>Parliament will alter Religion.</hi> A charge like that of <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> againſt <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> and as true. When he would perſwade the people <hi>God,</hi> would not helpe them: becauſe <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had <hi>altered Religion. Iſaias</hi> 36.7. If <hi>thou ſay to me we truſt in the Lord our God; is it not he whoſe Altars &amp; high places Hezekiah hath taken away &amp; ſayd to Iudah and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem you ſhall worſhip before this altar?</hi> Truth is. This is <hi>all the alteration of Religion</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath made. They have <hi>taken away the high places and Altars:</hi> that they have done &amp; <hi>intended</hi> to <hi>proceed</hi> to <hi>command all worſhip</hi> to be according to the <hi>rule of Gods word.</hi> To ſay to <hi>England, you ſhall worſhip according to this rule.</hi> And <hi>this is</hi> he great crime of altering <hi>Religion.</hi> My brethren be not deceived.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tio Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riva. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiva.</note> As in <hi>naturall</hi> ſo in <hi>civill</hi> and <hi>morall things</hi> there is a <hi>double alteration.</hi> There is a <hi>perfective alteration.</hi> And there is a <hi>corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive alteration.</hi> To alter <hi>Religion</hi> ſo as <hi>to corrupt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> was the <hi>plot</hi> and <hi>work</hi> of the <hi>Popiſh Prelats</hi> and <hi>their faction.</hi> To alter their <hi>alterations,</hi> to antiquate their <hi>innovations,</hi> to <hi>reduce Religion,</hi> to its <hi>pure originall perfection</hi> (which cannot be done without <hi>alteration</hi> of ſome thing <hi>introduced</hi>) that was the purpoſe and work of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and for this it is <hi>our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries crie against them. They will alter Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I but then the <hi>Parliament</hi> will alter the <hi>government of the Kingdome.</hi> Yes. Juſt like as they <hi>altered Religion.</hi> As in <hi>Religion</hi> ſuch <hi>alterations</hi> as tend <hi>Ad perfectionem</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:112489:39"/>are not to be condemned: So likewiſe in <hi>Polity</hi> and <hi>civill</hi> government. <hi>Plato</hi> tells us, That in all <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths</hi> upon juſt grounds there ought to be ſome changes. And that Statesmen therein muſt beehave themſelves like ski<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l Muſicians, <hi>Qui artem Muſices non mutant, ſed Muſices modum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But they do things without <hi>his Majesties conſent.</hi> I that is our greif and <hi>our adverſaries triumph.</hi> That <hi>our adverſaries</hi> have ſo farre prevailed upon the heart of our ſoveraign as to perſwade him to with draw <hi>first his preſence,</hi> then his <hi>aſſent</hi> from the great <hi>Councell</hi> of his <hi>Kingdome.</hi> And thereby force them, Either to do things without the conſent of our ſoveraign, Or elſe, do nothing, but <hi>ſit still,</hi> and <hi>expect their owne,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Kingdomes ruine</hi> And in ſuch a caſe is it ſo <hi>high acrime</hi> to determine things, <hi>neceſſary for the ſafety of King and Kingdome,</hi> without <hi>conſent of his Majeſtie</hi> when it <hi>cannot</hi> be obtained? I have read that the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Monarches</hi> were wont to call <hi>the Peers,</hi> and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents</hi> of their <hi>Provinces</hi> to <hi>Councell;</hi> but giving them no <hi>freedome</hi> nor <hi>liberty</hi> of <hi>Councell.</hi> For every one of them had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>plate,</hi> or <hi>tile of gold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> to ſtand upon in the <hi>Councell houſe</hi> and if he gave councell that the <hi>King thought well</hi> of,<note place="margin">Kecker Polit.</note> the plate of gold was <hi>given him for a reward: but if he</hi> delivered any thing <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>the Kings minde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Valer. Maxim. l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Flagris caedebatur</hi> And one writes that <hi>Xerxes</hi> in his expedition againſt <hi>Greece</hi> called his <hi>Princes together,</hi> and ſpake to them to this purpoſe. Leaſt, ſaith he, I ſhould ſeeme to <hi>follow only my owne Councell,</hi> I have <hi>aſſembled you,</hi> and now do you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member; <hi>that it becomes you</hi> rather <hi>to obey,</hi> then <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe. Our adverſaries</hi> would faine have it ſo with the <hi>Peers</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> and have a long
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:112489:40"/>time bin <hi>labouring to perſwade his Majeſtie</hi> it ought ſo to be, and would <hi>make the like impreſsion</hi> upon the <hi>people</hi> now. But you my <hi>brethren</hi> beware of their <hi>inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations</hi> and know. That they that devide <hi>between his Majeſtie</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> or between <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>people</hi> are the greateſt enemies of <hi>King, people,</hi> and <hi>Parliament.</hi> This is the <hi>firſt time</hi> that ever <hi>loyalty</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> was ſet <hi>in oppoſition</hi> to <hi>fidelity</hi> to the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> The <hi>firſt time</hi> that ever it was thought <hi>poſsible</hi> to draw the <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> to deſert their <hi>Parliament</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>notion of adhering</hi> to <hi>their King.</hi> Oh let not <hi>this age beare</hi> the date of ſuch <hi>infamy.</hi> Did ever <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> do more for the <hi>Lawes,</hi> and <hi>liberties</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> with more <hi>danger</hi> and <hi>detriment</hi> to <hi>themſelves:</hi> And will you when they have need of you leave them: well here is our comfort: <hi>God</hi> hath not <hi>left, God will not leave</hi> his <hi>cauſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings</hi> 8.57.58.59.60.</note> his <hi>work,</hi> his <hi>people.</hi> 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 8. <hi>The Lord our God be with us as he was with our fathers: let him not leave us nor forſake us; that he may encline our hearts unto him to walke in all his wayes and to keep his commandements and his Statutes and his Iudgements: He,</hi> even <hi>he maintaine the cauſe of his ſervants and of his people Iſraël at all times as the Matter ſhall require that all the people of the earth may know that the Lord is God and that there is none elſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:112489:40"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
